<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Higayon selah. Ierusalem fatall to her assailants. Discovered in a sermon before the Honorable House of commons August 29. 1649. At Margarets Westminster, upon their solemne day of thanksgiving for that signall victory over the Lord Ormond, in routing his whole army, and raising the seige of Dublin in Ireland, by the garrison thereof under the command of lieutenant Generall Jones. / By William Cooper M.A. minister of the gospel at Olaves Southwark.</title>
            <author>Cooper, William, minister at St. Olave's Southwark.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6064</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E572_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206160</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865337</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865337</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117577</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80426)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117577)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 88:E572[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Higayon selah. Ierusalem fatall to her assailants. Discovered in a sermon before the Honorable House of commons August 29. 1649. At Margarets Westminster, upon their solemne day of thanksgiving for that signall victory over the Lord Ormond, in routing his whole army, and raising the seige of Dublin in Ireland, by the garrison thereof under the command of lieutenant Generall Jones. / By William Cooper M.A. minister of the gospel at Olaves Southwark.</title>
                  <author>Cooper, William, minister at St. Olave's Southwark.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by  J.C. for the author, and are to be sold at the Crown in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first two words of the title are printed in Hebrew characters.</note>
                  <note>The verso of the fisrt leaf contains an order to print.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August 30".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117577:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>:חגיון סלה IERUSALEM Fatall to her Aſſailants. DISCOVERED In a Sermon before the Honorable Houſe of <hi>COMMONS</hi> Auguſt 29. 1649. At MARGARETS Weſtminſter, Vpon their ſolemne day of thankſgiving for that ſignall Victory over the Lord ORMOND, In routing his whole Army, and raiſing the Siege of <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> By the Garriſon thereof under the Command of Lieutenant Generall IONES. By WILLIAM COOPER M. A. Miniſter of the Goſpel at OLAVES Southwark.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 9.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Lord is known by the judgement that he executeth: The wicked is ſnared in the work of his own hands. <hi>Higgaion Selah.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Claud. lib. 1. in Eutrop.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>Sic opifex tauri, tormentorum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> repertor,</l>
               <l>Primus inexpertum, Siculo cogente tyranno;</l>
               <l>Senſit opus, docetque ſuum mugire juvencum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>London Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for the Author, and are to be ſold at the Crown in Popes-head Alley. 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:117577:2"/>
            <opener>
               <date>Die Iovis 30 Auguſti 1649.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>ORDERED by the <hi>Commons</hi> aſſembled in Parliament; that the thanks of this Houſe be given to M. <hi>Cooper</hi> for his great pains taken in his Sermon prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before this Houſe yeſterday at <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets</hi> Weſtminſter; being a day ſet a part for a publick Thanksgiving: And that he be deſired to print his Sermon; and have the like priviledge in printing as others uſually have had in the like caſe. And it is ordered that Sir <hi>Henry Mildmay</hi> doe give him the thanks of this Houſe accordingly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Henry Scobel</hi> Cler. Parliamenti.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:117577:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:117577:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117577:3"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Houſe of Commons aſſembled in Parliament at Weſtminſter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honorable Worthies,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Romans,</hi> what out of policie, or ſuperſtition,<note place="margin">Pluc. &amp; Macrob. Vide Caſp. Bart. ad Rutil. l. 2. v. 42.</note> made it heinous and capitall to make known the name of their Cities tutelar God, by whoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour Rome had attained to that height of gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and glory; it was religion to them to be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and ſecret in this: But our ſilence would be ſo far from being ſacred, that it were a ſin and high prophaning the name of our tutelar God, the great God and Lord of Hoſts, not to publiſh and blaze his Name unto the world, eſpecially when himſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that he doth his wondrous works, that they may be had in everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remembrance. But when I conſider the ſullen ſilence and ingratitude of many, notwithſtanding ſo vaſt a confluence of mercies upon us with mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure preſſed down and running over, me thinkes it calls to mind what an Hebrew Writer complaines of in his time, that the Fathers had plowed,<note place="margin">R. Hag.</note> ſowen, reaped, fanned, and ſet bread upon the Table, but the children had not a mouth to eat it. Surely that's a fooliſh and a froward child, that ſees not how his heavenly Father hath provided for him, and yet wants a heart to value, and a mouth to proclaim his goodneſſe. The ſenſe of which alone prevailed upon my ſpirit, to attend the call of Divine Providence by you <hi>(Honourable Worthies)</hi> both firſt to ſpeake, and now to publiſh this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing homely diſcourſe. <hi>I believe, therefore have I ſpoken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was a noble acknowledgement in <hi>David</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>Thine, O Lord, is the greatneſſe, and the power, and the glory, and the victory, and the Majeſty: All things come of thee, and of thine own have we given thee.</hi> How then can we grudge to give God his homage and tribute,
<pb facs="tcp:117577:4"/> who hold all at the will of the Lord? Our thankefulneſſe what is it but the reflection of his own beames, and the eccho of his ſtrokes? ſtrokes laid on ſo home and heavy upon your adverſaries, as makes ſome of them with the Magicians, to confeſſe the finger of God.</p>
            <p>You (right honorable) have declared your high ſenſe of ſo tranſcendent a deliverance, and I hope it will not ſoon die with you, being ſo rich a preſent, and earneſt of future happineſſe. Yet know, this doth not pay all your debt, <hi>Creſcentibus donis, donorum creſcunt rationes,</hi> much is given you, and therefore much ſhall be required of you. So then, it is proper for your ſoules now to ask this queſtion, What ſhall I render, and how ſhall I ſtand under this weight of glory and mercy? A queſtion ſo much the more proper and ſeaſonable, as our frailties are apt to expoſe us in proſperous ſucceſſes, unto the power of temptations; inſomuch as a ſage Heathen tels us this obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his,<note place="margin">Cicero, lib. 4. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. 3. ad Lam.</note> that although warre be full of calamities, yet nothing is more dangerous than victory, which albeit it happen to the beſt men, yet it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly renders them fierce, and impotent in their exceſſes; yea, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they are otherwiſe by nature inclined, yet by a kind of fatality they are made ſuch. The conſideration of this, I hope, will over-aw your hearts by a holy feare and watchfulneſſe, not onely to ſhun theſe rockes of extremity, to which you ſee men in ſuch a caſe obnoxious, but alſo to ſtudy an improvement of your mercies ſutable to the greatneſſe of them.</p>
            <p>There is a memorable ſtory of that grave Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, a man cut out for greatneſſe and happineſſe, had he not daſhed upon that rock which commonly ſplits Royal Families, an endevour to ſmother the Goſpel by force, and fraud; this man upon ſome ſucceſſes, was flattered by <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Leva,</hi> and ſome other of his officers, to make uſe of his victories for the advantage and intereſt of his Imperiall Majeſty, their meaning was, that he ſhould thereby make himſelf great, after the example of <hi>Caeſar</hi> &amp; <hi>Alexander,</hi> not ſparing any that ſtood in his way. To whom he thus reply'd, The ſole mark of <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>J. Caeſars</hi> aim,<note place="margin">Beſold. Diſſert. Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. &amp;c.</note> was worldly glory; but it becomes me, and other Chriſtian Princes, ſo to look at honour, as to take heed leſt while we hunt after that, we loſe our ſoules; and to uſe victory ſo, as we may be able to give God an account of our actions. This anſwer from ſuch a man at ſuch a time, I confeſſe made ſome impreſſion upon me, when I read it, my prayers are, it may doe more upon you, whom for your preſent capacity and tranſactions it more fitly ſuits.</p>
            <p>Shew thou your ſelves to God, as he hath declared himſelfe to you: Wot you how? In righteouſnes and holines, by theſe two the Lord makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf glorious, and theſe two will be as the two pillars <hi>Jachin</hi> and <hi>Boaz</hi> both
<pb facs="tcp:117577:4"/> to your own honour, and the happines of this people. For Religion,<note place="margin">Bodin. val. in Reſ. Hac ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lnti thyrſo percuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur mentes humanae Lib. 2. cap. 18. de prin.</note> I know a name only of it is ſufficient to ſome to maintain their own name, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve an intereſt. This hath been eſteemed by Princes ſufficient to charme and reſtrain the multitudes, foraſmuch as Religion hath the ſtrongeſt reaſon in it and for it, of all things. But if there be but a name, if there be but a ſhew, and ſingleneſſe in this, the Lord will not be mocked: Yet if any ſhould tell me, that <hi>England</hi> hath the ſame ground to complaine of what <hi>France</hi> did long agoe, That too many of their Chiefes had learned that Maxime of the <hi>Florentine</hi> Atheiſt, That as it was neceſſary for a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, ſo enough to ſeem religious outwardly, though inwardly hee were not ſo; I would not give credit to him upon this ground, becauſe it is impoſſible that thoſe viſible and ſignall diſcoveries of God to us in all the wayes of his diſpenſations, ſhould ſuffer us to impoſe upon his omniſcience. Beſides, me-thinks you often ſignifie, that religion is a tender Virgin, that muſt be as watchfully kept, as warily approached: The firſt of theſe, will mind you, that men be not ſuffered to run wild in the things of God: The other, that conſcience be not impoſed on by one or t'other hand The firſt is a Gallioniſme, the other is Antichriſtianiſme. I know none ſhall ever have juſt cauſe to faſten either of theſe upon your counſels or actions; for the one, who durſt preſume but that the name of God ſhall be as tender to you, as your own: for the other, that of <hi>Tertullian</hi> is obſervable, <hi>Hoc ad irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gioſitatis elogium concurrit adimere libertatem religionis, &amp; interdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere opinionem divinitatis, ut non liceat mihi colere quem velim, ſed cogar colere quem nolim.</hi> In a word, therefore endevour by ſteering a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right betwixt theſe two rocks, to preſerve our veſſell from ſhip-wrack; and let peace between brethren be ſo endevoured y you, which doth as it were pitch the ſhip within and without, that no leaks or chinks ſhal ſink it. Great <hi>Conſtantine</hi> did think it his duty and intereſt to perſwade and urge this by his perſonal preſence, &amp; authority. O you Fathers of your Country, conſider your children, ſome are ſtronger, ſome younger, ſome more heavy and ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, others more ſprightly and wanton; there are not onely diverſities, but diviſions among them. Put forth your authority with wiſdom and tenderneſſe effectually, that we may not alwayes bite and devoure one another. I ſhall adde this, Let intereſt of State ſway nothing to the calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of religion to any point. Notable is that example of <hi>Scipio Ammira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> upon <hi>Tacitus,</hi> Sith there is no proportion between temporall things and ſpirituall, when thou ſeeſt Religion to oppoſe thy reaſon of State, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently betake thy ſelfe to religion, and accommodate thy reaſon of State to that, and not the contrary: for if you think to lay a yoak upon the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:117577:5"/> of men, and thereby as a ſtrong man endevour to keep the Houſe in peace, they will anſwer you with that ſtout <hi>Pretor,</hi> O ye Romans we reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence you; and if you will have more, we feare you too; yet know, we beare a greater reverence and feare to the immortall Gods. Look therefore to this.</p>
            <p>The other Pillar of your name, and of your ſafety, is Righteouſneſſe: Read over thoſe innumerable Petitions written and unwritten of a long time, and yet daily preſented; lay your eares to the ſighes and teares of the oppreſſed that have no comforter, take heed that none juſtly appeale to the day of judgement from you, or againſt you; remember that your duty is by a Geometrical proportion to give to every one his right according to his capacity and merit, and to doe as you would be done by: ſometime to part with your plenty by contribution, and to abate of your height by condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to exigence. <hi>Salvian</hi> perſwading to this very thing, brings in the <hi>Fabii, Fabricii,</hi> and <hi>Cincinnati,</hi> who refuſed the advantage of grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rich,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Pro.</note> that if it were poſſible by their impoveriſhment they might raiſe the ruines of a ſhattered Common-wealth. But that of <hi>Philo</hi> is notable, who ſaith, <hi>Jupiter</hi> had two Twins, to one of them he gave immortality, the other he made mortall: the brother that was immortall conſidering his own life to be endleſſe, and that his brother ſhould die, and ſo his griefe for his brothers death would conſequently be eternal, deviſed this marvellous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, he communicated immortality with his mortall brother, by which both had a mixture of both. This he calls the fountain and ground of all Juſtice. Some will be ready to apply this againſt the immortallity of your preſent Seſſion, me thinks it clearly tells all, whom God hath for a turn lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up above their brethren, that they declare a communicableneſſe with their brethren. My aim (Worthies) was but this, that by the flouriſhing of Religion and Righteouſneſſe among you and us. I may congratulate my Countrey with this acclamation, <hi>The Lord bleſſe thee, O habitation of juſtice, and mountain of holineſſe,</hi> Jer. <hi>31.23.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This mean Sermon here again preſented, together with the occaſion, ſerves for a comfortable encouragement in the premiſes, by ſhewing the ſelf-deſtroying enterprizes of your enemies, how fatall Jeruſalem is to her aſſailants, how faithfull the Lord is in his engagements for his people. That emergency which gave occaſion to our ſolemnity, and this diſcourſe, beares teſtimony to ſo weighty a truth. Now that our hearts may come up to it in our reſpective places and duties, is the prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours daily Orator at the Throne of Grace,</hi> William Cooper</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117577:5"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached before the Houſe of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Zach. 12.2, 3, 4, 5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Behold, I will make <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> a cup of poyſon unto all the people round about: alſo with <hi>Iudah</hi> will he be in the ſiege againſt <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And in that day will I make <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> an heavy ſtone for all people: all that lift it up ſhall be torn, though all the people of the earth be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together againſt it.</p>
                  <p>In that day, ſaith the Lord, I will ſmite every horſe with aſtoniſhment, and his rider with madneſſe, and I will open mine eyes upon the houſe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and will ſmite every horſe of the people with blindeneſſe.</p>
                  <p>And the Princes of <hi>Iudah</hi> ſhall ſay in their hearts, The inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhall be my ſtrength in the Lord of hoſts their God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right honourable and beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O day is this word fulfilled to us; this propheſie is but a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, or repreſentative of mercy, if our hearts doe but an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer unto both; and if our thankfulnes come but up to theſe words, and to theſe works of God, it will be a pleaſing har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in Gods ears: Which that it may bee, I am now here by your Call, to contribute a little out of my penury, to what you had but now ſo largely and ſo lively ſet before your eyes. God hath this day turned our Faſt into a Feaſt, and this as ſolemne for praiſe and mirth, as that was ſolemne for prayer and mourning; thus he alone can change the ſeaſons and the occaſions, and calls to us anſwerably to change the key of our devotions: there is a time to weep and a time to laugh; we have had both; and the firſt preparing for, and changed into the latter, through the precious mercyes of our God, who is yet good to our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and hath not left himſelf without witnes to us, as at this day. That I might further hold out God in his glory to you, and hold up your hearts to take a full ſurvey of it; I have endeavoured to ſeek out a ſeaſonble and ſutable word: for we may know, as there's nothing new under the Sun; ſo the providence of God which hath wrought hitherto, worketh yet ſtill for his Church; and ſo will doe yet more gloriouſly, that yee all may marvell.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:117577:6"/>
            <p>Obſerve then the parts and parralel together: You have here, firſt, a very formall, and formidable laying a ſiege; ſecondly, We have a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall raiſing of that ſiege: thirdly, we have the cauſes and conſequents of both: In the firſt, two things are conſiderable,</p>
            <p>Firſt, The beſieged, ſecondly, the beſiegers.</p>
            <p>The Beſieged is a City, no mean City; but a Mother in <hi>Iſrael, Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> the metropolis of <hi>Judea,</hi> the glory of the earth; the City of God is inveſted, and beleagured; the beloved City is ſurrounded and ſtraightned by her adverſaryes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Beſiegers; a numerous Hoſt, all the people round about; ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Nations, bad neighbours, ſuch as bear evill will to <hi>Sion;</hi> all theſe come up againſt <hi>Juda</hi> and againſt <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> this is clearly implyed, <hi>v.</hi> 2. Nay its preſuppoſed, that all the people of the earth may deſigne a ſiege, and ſacking to <hi>Jeruſalem, v</hi> 3. Beſides, they ſhall come up well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided with Horſe and Foot, and all warlike equipage, and they ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance ſo far, as to attach it, they ſhall be lifting at it, preſuming to carry it, <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3, 4. compared together: Thus much of the ſiege of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſignall raiſing of the ſiege:</p>
            <p>Wherein obſerve we firſt, the Cauſes: ſecondly, the conſequents: The Cauſes are twofold, Principall, and inſtrumentall: the principall cauſe of this work of Deliverance and Victory, for its both, is the Lord <hi>Jehovah,</hi> who appears chief in this action, in every verſe to the eighth, and he is deſcribed by his power and by his will, which are put forth to relieve and ſuccour <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Particularly, the Lord comes forth armed with his Almighty creating power, deſcribed in there eminent ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it, ſtretching out the heavens, laying the foundation of the earth, and forming the ſpirit of man within him: This is to tell you how far the Lord <hi>Jehovah</hi> will engage for the reſcuing of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in diſtreſs, his wonder-working, and world creating power.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Inſtrumentall cauſe of <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> reliefe, for the Lord makes uſe of Inſtruments in it; and that is, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> it ſelf ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentall in its own deliverance; and the Lord thus working for <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> by <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> puts forth ſeverall acts in the manner of his working, here elegantly expreſſed, and happily taking effect upon the enemy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Infatuating of him, he would needs drink a cup, and he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicated with it, <hi>v.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Worſting or breaking them; he would be lifting and heaving at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and this ſtone fell upon him and brake him, <hi>v.</hi> 3.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117577:6"/>
            <p n="3">3. By aſtoniſhing the Horſe and his ryder, their moſt active powers, their Cavalry and flower:</p>
            <p n="4">4. After this follows the enemies utter conſumption; <hi>all of them ſhall be cut in pieces, and conſumed as ſtraw with fire,</hi> v. 3, 6. Thus we have the Cauſes. Hence,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Follow the effects and conſequents.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is delivered and ſecured:</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hereupon follows the doxology, high and low, governours and inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſpeak hearty praiſe to the Lord of Hoſts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging wherein their ſtrength lyes, in the Lord and his people; and withall we have an act of faith in the governours, reſolving to make choice of the Lord of Hoſts for their protector, cleaving to him, and being aſſured of him upon this ſcore and intereſt, that they have the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> with them and for them, <hi>i. e.</hi> Gods people, who have alwayes Gods preſence and power by which they are invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible, <hi>v.</hi> 5. Thus you have the Lords doing, and our duty.</p>
            <p>Theſe are our parts, and the parallel is clear between <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> caſe and this occaſion; it needs not further repetition or application: for as the words ſeem litterally meant of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> aſſaulted and diſtreſſed by <hi>Antiochus,</hi> defended and relieved by the <hi>Maccabees;</hi> ſo is it myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally meant of the Chriſtian Church, or any part of it, perſecuted by <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt</hi> and his powers of whom <hi>Antiochus</hi> was no obſcure type or fore-runner.<note n="*" place="margin">The inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Gods people in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and the enemies rage againſt it, together with the righteous in it, may well intitle ſuch another City, <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Now, oh that the other part of the Propheſie <hi>v.</hi> 8. were fulfilled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us this day as it was upon them; that in that day, <hi>i. e.</hi> when God puts forth his power in and for his people; then the inhabitants of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and he that is feeble among them ſhall be as <hi>David,</hi> and the houſe of <hi>David</hi> as God, and as the Angel of God before him; they have been in power and valour: Oh let us be as <hi>Davids,</hi> and as Angels in praiſe and thankſgiving: Had we but <hi>Davids</hi> heart and harp, we might ſing upon thoſe parts of the text, a Pſalm of <hi>Degrees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I muſt crave leave to paſſe through the Porch and Entry, to my Text, the firſt verſe of the Chapter is but a preparatory preface to that I pitch upon for our meditations; yet hath it ſome influence and relation to that which follows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The burden of the word of the Lord for <hi>Iſrael: Thus ſaith the Lord that ſtretched forth the heavens, that laid the foundations of the earth, that formeth the ſpirit of man within him</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, This Song or comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table propheſie begins with the burden firſt; a burden that doth not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117577:7"/> pinch or preſſe Gods people at all, tis for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for their ſakes, for their ſafety, for their comfort: but a burden indeed faln heavy upon <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> enemies, <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> beſiegers; this burden is theirs.</p>
            <p>Its a common metaphor among the Prophets, importing ſome judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or propheticall threatning of judgement upon a people; ſuch a contrariety is there between <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and her enemyes: that as the two ſcales of a balance, put weight in one, it preſſeth down, and lifts the other up: the riſe of <hi>Sion</hi> is the fall of <hi>Babylon;</hi> the death of the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes makes the inhabitants of the earth merry, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11.10. When <hi>Ieremy</hi> and his people lamented in tears, their enemyes laughed, mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at their Sabbaths. Againe, the Saints have their turn at laſt, they ſhall laugh laſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.13, 14. <hi>Behold, my ſervants ſhall rejoyce, but yee ſhall be aſhamed; my ſervants ſhall ſing for joy of heart, but yee ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and howle for vexation of Spirit.</hi> Revel. Now this is a ſpeciall act of divine juſtice, to give every one his turn; and not onely ſo, but by the law of retaliation, to make his people ſhift their burdens upon their oppreſſours ſhoulders: <hi>The burdens that oppreſſors lay on the back of the righteous, ſhall fall heavy upon themſelves, break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their bones, and preſſing them down into the Pit.</hi> This they get by laying load on the Saints of God: but of that afterward from the 3. <hi>v.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>The burden of the word of the Lord.</q>
            <p>The word fals heavy upon ſinners, though they make light of it: this expreſſion was ſo familiar among the Prophets, in the degenerate time of the Church; that the obſtinate Jews would come in ſcorn, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.33, 14, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> what is the burden of the Lord? but they found it a burden to them indeed. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> made light of Gods threats and plagues on him by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron;</hi> but at laſt they ſunck him as a ſtone to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Sea. <hi>Ahab</hi> made light of <hi>Michaiahs</hi> word, but it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a heavy burden to <hi>Ahab,</hi> as <hi>Iehu</hi> cals it. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9.25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The burden of the word of the Lord for</hi> Iſrael, <hi>i. e.</hi> This vengeance threatned on the beſiegers, is for <hi>Iſraels</hi> ſake, in favour of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> All the havock that he makes of great perſons, of families, of whole Cities, Armies, Nations, is for <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the whole current of Gods judgements is but a comment and confirmation of this; pertinent to this and very pregnant is that of the Prophet;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> when he tells <hi>Iſrael</hi> there, as here; <hi>that he was his maker, redeemer, and preſerver from all evils:</hi> he gives the reaſon of all, <hi>verſe</hi> 3, 4. <hi>I am the Lord thy God, the holy one of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>thy Saviour: I gave</hi> Egypt <hi>for thy ranſome,</hi> Ethiopia <hi>and</hi> Seba <hi>for thee, ſince thou waſt precious in my ſight, thou haſt been honourable, and I have loved thee; therefore will I give men for thee, &amp; people for thy ſake.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117577:7"/> The Lord takes away multitudes of wicked men as droſſe, and counts them but as the dung of the Earth for</hi> Iſrael. What a diſtinguiſhing love is here in a gracious God, that puts ſo vaſte a difference between men and men; between party and party, accounting his own honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, his enemies baſe; his own precious, his enemies vile: The Lord like a Lion goes forth and tears what ever he meets with, to feed his young, be it men or beaſts. Thus the Lord makes bloody ſacrifices and ſlaughters his adverſaries bee they never ſo mighty or many;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.17, 18, 19.</note> as we have it notably deſcribed by <hi>Iohn</hi> in the <hi>Revelations; Having armed and mounted Ieſus Chriſt with royall conquering power, brings in the Angel, inviting all to a great feaſt, which he cals the ſupper of God; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion is fleſh, coſtly fleſh; to eat the fleſh of Kings, the fleſh of Captains, the fleſh of mighty men of hoſts; and them that ſit on them, &amp;c.</hi> I do not take the words litterally of Birds feeding on the carkaſſes of the churches ſlaughtered enemies lying unburied, though that may be too; but of warriours mingling themſelves with the Church for pay and prey; or of militant Saints, who being married to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> as conquerours; hee ſups them upon the ſpoiles of their enemies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74.14.</note> the mighty <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemoths</hi> and <hi>Leviathans</hi> that prey on Sea and Land; the inſatiable Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates of the Earth, <hi>even they ſhall be meat for his people,</hi> as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> ſaid, <hi>the mighty</hi> Anachs <hi>ſhould be bread for</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Num.</hi> 14.9. Thus out of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> comes forth meat, and out of the ſtrong commeth ſweetneſſe; the Lord will make the Lion that wars againſt <hi>Sampſon</hi> to fall by his hands, he ſhall tear him as a Kid, and the carkaſſe of him ſhall yeeld <hi>Sampſon</hi> honey.</p>
            <q>Saith the Lord which ſtretcheth forth the Heavens, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>Then the Lord comes forth armed as a God, he puts on all his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and all his might when he engages for <hi>Ieruſalem: then he awakes as a great Lyon, and as a Gyant refreſhed with Wine; Then the hils melt, and the earth trembles at his preſence, when he commeth forth to ayde</hi> Jeruſalem; for then he commeth forth like a God, that is, like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; the Lord will put forth no leſſe grandour and glory in delivering <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> then when he made the world: <hi>Let all, ſaith God, be redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a Chaos of confuſion,</hi> ſuch ſeemed once our condition, and now little better to thoſe that cannot or will not ſee; yet I will fetch order out of that, ſaith the Lord: <hi>Let all be covered over with darkneſſe,</hi> and jumbled into rubbiſh; nay, let all be ſhut up again, into the wombe of nothing, at leaſt that nothing of inhability, improbability, and impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility too, as to a created agent; yet I will create deliverance, fetch out a coſmos, a beautifull pile, and face of things: praiſe the Lord in this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117577:8"/> great laſt reſtauration of the world, which we truſt is now beginning. <hi>The Lord will make a new heaven and a new earth,</hi> Revel. 21.1. The Lord will make quite another world, and all this for <hi>Iſrael. Have you not heard, hath it not been told you, that it is I, and onely I doe this; that I make nothing of my peoples enemies, be they many, a whole world of them,</hi> as verſ. 3. Yet I ſpread out the heavens while they beſiege then <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> i'le overwing their multitudes, i'le front them and flanck them; I will catch them all in a Net, for I ſtretch out the heavens: and for their power, their mining, their confidence; let them look to their ground, I lay the foundations of the earth; let them dig as deep as hell to hide counſell, and to ſhake thy wals, and caſt thee down O <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> I will countermine them, I'le blow them quite up, they ſhall be buried in their own rubbiſh, ſaith the Lord: what if they abound with courage and malice inſomuch that my people are even afraid of them? is it not I that form the ſpirit of man within him; I take and give courage, I will make thee ſtout-hearted as women, but I will make them that are feeble among my people, as <hi>David,</hi> for I form the ſpirit of man within him: And for the Savage diſpoſition of the enemy, I tame that ſaith God; Daniel <hi>and the Lyons ſhall lodge quietly together, my Lambs ſhall feed ſafely among the Bears and Wolves, my Children ſhall play with Aſpes and Cockatrices, for I form the ſpirit of man within.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Right honourable and beloved,</hi> Here's matter of courage and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for us; here's ground not of prayer onely, but of praiſe this day. Was not the enemy ſweld with that height of arrogance and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon his numbers and advantages; had he not ſo neer compaſſed and carried <hi>Dublin,</hi> as to ſay, it could not be delivered out of his hands without a miracle: Loe! our Creator hath wrought this miracle, when he that ſtretcheth out the heavens, &amp;c. undertakes it; he can doe it, and hath done it; and did he ever appear like a God for us yet more, then in this engagement: ſo few and feeble againſt ſo many and mighty, 1200 Horſe, and not the third part of 4000 Foot in the act on, conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring 19000 and beyond their own purpoſes and thoughts to charge the whole Army, yet carried on! Thus if the ſpirit of the Lord come on <hi>Sampſon</hi> he ſhall break his cords, and ſlay heapes upon heapes with an Aſſes jaw-bone, but let us not anticipate: Here have yee ſeen the Lord of Hoſts armed like himſelf: now hear the Herauld ſounding the trumpet before him in the next verſe, <hi>Behold, I will make</hi> Ieruſalem <hi>a cup of trembling, &amp;c.</hi> I thus armed, thus reſolved, will now ſhew my glory at this great undertaking; come and ſee a famous ſpectacle, your God
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117577:8"/> engaging for <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> when the Lord once engageth eminently for <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to defend and deliver it,<note place="margin">Note.</note> he ſummons all to be ſpectatour and obſervers of it. Before he ſhewed his power what he could doe, here he declares his will, what he is reſolved to doe. <hi>Behold, I will make, &amp;c.</hi> a ſolemne ſummons.</p>
            <p>This is worth noting, God looks to be obſerved and admired in his great workings for a diſtreſſed people, he cals for it aloud. Revel. 6. <hi>When the Lamb opened the firſt ſeale,</hi> John <hi>ſaith, he heard a noiſe as of thunder, one of the foure beaſts, ſaying, Come and ſee; and when he had opened the ſecond ſeale, I heard the ſecond beaſt ſay, Come and ſee: And when he had opened the third ſeale, I heard the voyce of the third beaſt, ſay, Come and ſee: And when he had opened the fourth ſeale, I heard the fourth beaſt, Come and ſee;</hi> Alloquitur <hi>Ioannem</hi> ſuſtinentem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonam fidelis populi qui ſimiliter per vocem miniſtrorum excitarentur ad obſervandos hos mirabiles eventus. <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Moſes</hi> told trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling <hi>Iſrael, Feare not ſtand ſtill and ſee the ſalvation of God, which he will ſhew you this day;</hi> The Lord ſhall fight for you, and yee ſhall hold your peace: yea, that's a glorious ſight to ſee indeed, to ſee God taking a <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in hand, of whom wee ſaid, <hi>For this cauſe have I raiſed thee up to ſhew in thee my power, and that my name may be declared through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the earth.</hi> This is one main end, why the Lord fats and heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens an adverſary, that he may try miſteries with him, and ſpend his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows on him; and all this, to be obſerved and admired the more. Pſal. 111 2. <hi>The works of the Lord are great, ſought out of all that have pleaſure therein:</hi> his work is honourable and glorious, he hath made his wonderfull works to be remembred, that's their end: the Lord would never appear upon the ſtage, if he had not ſome ſtrange act to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; he would never call inſpectatours, if he would not provide ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what worth ſeeing.</p>
            <p>This hath made the Saints in all ages curious in obſerving Gods works. <hi>Abraham</hi> rejoyced in ſeeing Chriſts day: <hi>Iacob</hi> waited for Gods ſalvation, <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaid, <hi>I beſeech thee ſhew me thy glory;</hi> he had ſeen much of God before, all that did but whet his appetite, he was ſtill greedy after more. <hi>Daniel</hi> was a man of deſires in this ſenſe, as you heard it gloſſed but now, and had a large proſpect, yet would fain have crowded to ſee more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Right honourable,</hi> You ſet us to diſplay God in his grandour this day, you ſtand upon advantageous ground, and you ſee farre and quick into Gods works; for you have declared your ſenſe of this and former mercies: yet you will yeeld, you have not ſeen all, and that its worth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117577:9"/> reading, and turning over and over this marvellous diſcovery and diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of God: Say then with <hi>Moſes,</hi> when the buſh burned and was not conſumed, when the Church was in a flame, and yet flouriſhed in the fire; <hi>I will now turn about and ſee what this great ſight meaneth, Exod.</hi> 3.3. The Lord wonders and is very angry at the ſenleſneſſe and blindeneſſe of men, that will not ſee his hand lifted up: men that are quick witted, and ſharp ſighted in other things, they can diſcern the face of the skyes, but will not know the ſignes of the times, when they are viſible; but let the wicked doe wickedly, for none of them ſhall underſtand, but the wiſe ſhall underſtand: the ſcripture makes tother a matter of folly and brutiſhneſſe, but theſe providentiall acts upon wicked men in their ruffe, and when they flouriſh, and are preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous, then to pull them down, this is too deep for wicked men; yet are wee ſolemnly called to obſerve it; See <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14. <hi>ult. Pſal.</hi> 92 5, 6, 7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.40, 41, 42, 43.</p>
            <p>Behold, I will make <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> a cup of trembling to all the people round about, when they ſhall be in the ſiege, both againſt <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note, Ieruſalem</hi> may be beſieged by her enemies; the place and people of God may be encompaſſed and diſtreſſed by their Adverſaries; a truth ſo clear, both of litterall and myſticall <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that it is but time waſte to prove it.</p>
            <p>Its obſervable, that our three grand enemies, are encompaſſing ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and grow dangerous: For an enemy to encompaſſe, argues a four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold danger. Firſt, It argues neerneſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Superiority in power, elſe he neither could or durſt advance ſo cloſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Superiority in numbers, elſe he could not ſurround and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſe; for he that is without hath the largeſt Line.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, A diſtreſſe and ſtraitning from eſcape: all this is implyed in a ſiege.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Devill, <hi>Iob</hi> 1.7. <hi>Iob</hi> 2.2. <hi>He compaſſeth the earth;</hi> 1 Pet. 5.8. He is ſaid <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, to walk about, and to devour: There's not a ſoul of a righteous man, but he layes ſiege, making aſſaults and battery to that ſoule: as for the hearts of wicked men, he is poſſeſſed of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready; and they are fortified by him againſt God his Word, and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Sin is an encreaſing evill, its called ſin that doth eaſily beſet, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.5. <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his heels compaſſing him about.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:117577:9"/>
            <p n="3">3. The world none will doubt but that's an encompaſſing enemy. Therefore the poor Church is not only called a lilly among thorns, a ſpeckled Bird amongſt the Birds, Lambs among Wolves, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly a beſieged City, <hi>the Daughter of Sion is left as a Cottage in a Vineyard, as a Lodge in a Garden of Cucumbers, as a beſieged City.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 1.8.</note> Solitary and ſurrounded, and not only inveſted at large, but cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtreightned and diſtreſſed; ſo as with <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> they know not what to do, only their eyes, are upward towards God, <hi>reſtat iter coelo tantum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ground of this from God, is partly to give check, reſtraint to the extravagancies of his people, and we know ſometimes it is but need: the beſt and moſt retired ſoul hath his wanton flings,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and its very hard to keep it from leering and hankering after ſome vanity: to cure this the Lord will hedge us in with thornes,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Hoſ. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that we ſhall not find our lovers. We are apt to turn our liberty into licenciouſnes, and the grace of God into wantonnes, and to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit upon mercy, to growe fat and ranck, to begin to gone and kick, and break fence: the Lord ſees good to pinch us for this, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce us to our meaſure and compaſſe, by driving us into corners. <hi>Sic deus cohibet &amp; fraenat ſuos ne diffluant:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calvin.</note> thus the Lord will hamper his own; he will banck and bound them into their right Channels, leaſt they overflow their bancks; but this is chiefly to role on a proud enemy to preſumption, that while he thinks to try experiments, and do exploits upon <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> the Lord will lay ſnares and ambuſhes for him, the Lord will lead him on, and make his work ſeem facile and feiſable to him: he will give him ſome advantages, he ſhall begin to grow fat with ſome ſucceſſes, hee'l preſent him faire hopes of carrying the day, and glutting himſelf with ſpoyles: hee'l ſuffer the <hi>Lyon</hi> to get his prey into his Chambers, and between his teeth, playing with it ſecurely, and gaping to devoure: now all this is but to get <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> beyond retreat, and when I have him but in my net, then ſaith God, Il'e draw: now is my time to ſtir and work: now il'e look thorough the Cloud and pillar of fire, upon the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and trouble them; and there <hi>Pharaoh</hi> flies, but 'tis too late, ſtretch out thy hand <hi>Moſes,</hi> and let the waters cover <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his Hoſt, let him ſink and be buried in the mighty waves, the Lord will reduce his people beyond humane hopes of relief, and then he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117577:10"/> will be glorified, let <hi>Lazarus</hi> be ſick, and let him die, and let him be buried, and let him ſtinck: now ſaith Chriſt, my houre is come, Il'e go to <hi>Bethany</hi> and rayſe <hi>Lazarus:</hi> the Lord delivers a people out of the mouth of danger,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.34. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.16.17.</note> as <hi>David reſcued the Lamb and Kid out of the mouth of the Lyon and Beare; or as Abiſhai ſuccoured</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>when</hi> IſhbiBenob, <hi>a ſon of the Gyant, lift up his ſword to have ſlain</hi> David, <hi>then</hi> Abiſhai <hi>flew him; or as when Saul had compaſſed David round, that there was but a ſtop between him &amp; death, and a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger came and diverted Saul: thus will the Lord judge his people, when he ſeeth their ſtrength is gone,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.36.</note> 
               <hi>when there is none ſhut up or left:</hi> when his people are full of miſ-giving, diſ-maying feares, when their Anchor breaks, and their Faith failes, when every countenance is caſt down, and every corner is full of murmurings, when <hi>Ziglag</hi> is burnt and all taken, and <hi>David</hi> weeps till there be no more ſtrength, and his men talk of ſtoning of him too, at that inſtant ſhall he march and God before him,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.31. <hi>cap.</hi>
               </note> to recover what's loſt, and ſpoyle the ſpoyler, and moreover, then <hi>Saul</hi> his capital enemy is deſtroyed Who ſo is wiſe will ponder this, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And was it not thus with <hi>Ireland?</hi> how near was that whole Land loſt, but two places, and thoſe ready to give up the Ghoſt, left? two little flocks of kids, and thoſe pent up too, while the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy filled the Countrey? when all was bent to revolting, and intended ſuccours not ready; when wagers were laid, and books out that <hi>Dublin</hi> was loſt, and <hi>Ireland</hi> loſt, and at the ſame time the people ſtriving and chiding with <hi>Moſes?</hi> Now will I come forth and work, ſaith God, now will I appear moſt gloriouſly, had I begun before, it had been too ſoone, and ſhould I delay longer, it would be too late: the adverſary is preſumptuous and ſecure, my people are low, and diſtreſſed enough. And how doth God work? It followes, I will make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a cup of trembling, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſpirit of God makes often uſe of this Metaphor of the cup, in the caſe of affliction,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.29.</note> puniſhment or judgment, <hi>our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf dranck his Cup, a very bitter one, wherein no creature could pledge him, i. e.</hi> in his meaſure; although every Child of God hath a portion of the cup of affliction, in conformity to our head, not to expiate ſin, or ſatisfie divine juſtice, yet oftentimes to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and purge ſin.</p>
            <p>The Saints have alſo another cup, a delicious one given them of God; the cup of bleſſing in the Euchariſt, that ſoul-refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117577:10"/> nectar, which the Lord Jeſus hath broached out of his own ſide.</p>
            <p>They have another delicious cup, which the Lord gives them into their mouthes, upon any great mercy and deliverance from their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which is the cup of Salvation: this was uſed in their ſacrifices and feaſts, and they were wont to lift it up,<note place="margin">Illyric.</note> and to pray and prayſe God with it, for victory and mercy, and it was a ſigne of freedom; This cup hath the Lord given us to drink, wherein we taſt and ſee how gracious he is to us, this he fils us to the brim, and makes it over-flow in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of our enemies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.5. But as for the wicked 'tis not ſo with them, the Lord hath tempered another kind of cup for them, of which our text ſpeakes: of this mention is made in <hi>Ezek.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.33</note> where the Lord tells <hi>Aholibah, i. e. Judah,</hi> that becauſe ſhe walked after the way of her Siſter <hi>Aholah, i. e. Samaria:</hi> therefore ſaith he, I will give her cup in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy hands, thus ſaith the Lord, thou ſhalt drink of thy Siſters cup, deep and large, thou ſhalt be laughed to ſcorn, and had in deriſion, it containeth much, thou ſhalt be filled with drunkennes and ſorrow, with the cup of aſtoniſhment and deſolation, with the cup of thy Siſter <hi>Samaria,</hi> thou ſhalt drink it, and ſuck it out, thou ſhalt even break the ſheards thereof, and pluck off thy breaſts, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſhalt carry thy ſelf as one that is mad drunck, who breaks pots and glaſſes, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf as one diſtracted: this is the ſore cup of judgment and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſtation.</p>
            <p>The like we have, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 25.15.16. where the Lord tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered a cup of fury, and makes <hi>Jeremie</hi> the modeperator to give every one his ſhare, they ſhall drinck, and be moved, and be mad, becauſe of the ſword which I will ſend among them, <hi>v.</hi> 27.28. and if you ſearch the cauſes why theſe Nations were puniſht: comparing this with other Scriptures, we ſhall ſee the quarrel to be that in the Text, they had plotted or laid hands againſt <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and 'tis for <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ſake this cup is given him?</p>
            <p>But what ground is there of this Metaphor, and uſage of the cup thus applyed</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some will have meant by cup, portion, or meaſure; every one at their ſeaſts was to take his <hi>dimenſum,</hi> or proportion: according to theſe, the phraſe ſignifies but this, every ſin ſhall have his degrees and ſhare in punniſhment, for cup ſignifies portion, or lot in Scripture.</p>
            <p>But this is too ſcanty for the queſtion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others will have it derived from witches and ſorcerers, which were wont to mingle intoxicating cups, and to ſophiſticate their wines, and the word in the text will bear it, for it ſignifies poyſon,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and hence the latine word <hi>veneſica.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:117577:11"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Hierome</hi> and ſome others, think it taken from a medicinal poti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſtrong Phyſick, which is ill to look on, and worſe to ſwallow down, being bitter, loathſome, and worſe to ſome Patients, then the diſeaſe, cauſing them to feele heart-qualmes, to ſtagger, and even ſwound away.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Beſides all theſe, there are who think it taken from condemned malefactors, whoſe friends were wont to temper them a cup of wine, for the reviving of their ſpirits, againſt exceſſive ſorrow and feare of death:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 16.7.</note> of this the Prophet ſeemes to ſpeak, when among other fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral rights, he ſaith, men ſhall not give them the cup of conſolation to drink for their Father or Mother, Thoſe that draw the Metaphor hence make it hold in this only, that thoſe that drank the cup of conſolation, were ſuch as were already condemned to die; and therefore it was a ſigne of judgment; but that in the Text ſeemes a cup, that the friends of them that were dead already, drunck to comfort themſelves, and to make them leſſe ſenſible of that loſſe: ours is not a cup of conſolation to our enemies, nor their friends; but a cup of trembling and aſtoniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Prada</hi> on <hi>Ezekiel</hi> though he ſeemed to incline to the other Expoſitions for a while, yet at laſt he cloſed with this as the moſt genuine, Namely, that there was a ſift ſort of cup, or drinking, which was in uſe at their great compotations, where the ſonnes of <hi>Bacchus</hi> ſtrove for Maſteries, who ſhould drink moſt, and every one was forced to take off his cup to the bottome; which was not ſo ſweet and pleaſant in the beginning, as it was loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome afterwards, as being too heavy a load for his natural ſtrength to bear, and therefore muſt ſinke under it; This is the contention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween divine Juſtice and the ſinner. A wicked man loves to drink the ſweet wine of pleaſure and luſt, to ſatisfy himſelf in his inordinate long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; but he refuſeth to drink out the bottome, where judgment and puniſhment alwaies lye, he loaths that; but oh ſaith God, its in vaine to ſtrive, thou ſhalt have the bottome too, thou canſt not draw off the Wine from the lees,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.8.</note> but thou ſhalt drink both. The Pſalmiſts expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeems to come home to this. <hi>In the hand of the Lord there is a cup, the Wine red,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Kimchi.</note> (the colour of the moſt generous Wines in Paleſtine, with which colour they were moſt inamoured and tempted, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.31.) <hi>it is full of mixture, and he powreth out of the ſame; but the dregs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, all the wicked of the earth ſhall wring them out and drink them.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit there ſeems ſomewhat more then this expoſition in that inſtance:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117577:11"/> The ſubſtance of the draught containes many ingredients; which is, variety of Gods judgements and wrath; and therefore ſome read for <hi>vinum, rubrum</hi> (red) <hi>turbidum</hi> (troubled Wine) thick, like, a confecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or medicinall potion; Take them altogether, we may draw out this, That the enemies of Gods people who thirſt to ſwallow them up, though this be ſweet to their palats; yet they ſhall have ſuch a Potion through Gods juſt fury and revenge, as ſhall make them ſick, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry themſelves as drunken men, and they ſhall periſh in this their drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe.</p>
            <p>The word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> tranſlatad by us trembling, in the text ſignifies luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, drunkenneſſe, ſtupidity, poyſon, and ſo is variouſly tendred, and it makes the ſence full: the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> alſo tranſlated cup, ſignifies a gate or threſhold, whence the vulgar renders it <hi>ſuperliminarie cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulae,</hi> the threſhold of ſurfeit, the <hi>Syriac,</hi> the gate of trembling,<note place="margin">Cor. the <hi>70.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Arabick,</hi> the gate of commotion, ſome, a cup of poyſon, this empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall pregnancy of the words gives us this ſumme: The enemy ſhall come and beſiege <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> they ſhall advance to the very gates, they ſhall ſet their foot on the threſhold, but there they ſhall ſtumble and fall; they ſhall come up greedily to ſwallow with open mouth, as a man hot and dry ſwallowes down a cup of refreſhing liquor, they ſhall thirſt for blood, treaſure, and ſpoyles,<note place="margin">Iſaiah. <hi>49.</hi> ult.</note> 
               <hi>but I will make them drunk with their own blood, as with ſweet wine, ſpoken of the Churches oppreſſors:</hi> as <hi>Thomyris</hi> told <hi>Cyrus,</hi> whoſe head ſhe cut off, and caſt into a veſſel of blood, ſaying this, Thou haſt ſlayn my Son, and didſt thirſt after my blood too; now ſatisfie thy ſelf with that thou didſt thirſt after. <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dot. &amp;c.</hi> The enemy that made ſo full account to ſwallow up <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> quick, when his wrath was kindled, is ſtupified and aſtoniſhed with that draught, its <hi>poculum ſoporis,</hi> a cup of drowſines to him:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.5.6.</note> Thus the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> expreſſeth it, <hi>The ſtout-hearted are ſpoyled, they have ſlept their ſleep, and none of the men of might have found their hands: At thy rebuke O God of</hi> Jacob, <hi>both the Chariot and horſe are caſt into a dead ſleep:</hi> as our Text hath it verſe 4. where the cup doth aſtoniſh the horſe and rider; and where was it the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier</hi> 25.15.16</note> this confuſion came on the enemy? at <hi>Salem, v.</hi> 3. <hi>there brake he the Arrowes,</hi> that made he ſuch a cup, that's one effect.</p>
            <p>Another is a cup of madnes, which is another effect of this cup, <hi>they ſhall drink, and be moved, and mad.</hi> It was ſaid of the Sybill of <hi>Cuma,</hi> that aſſoone as any ſtepped over her threſhold they began to rave,<note place="margin">Virg. <hi>6.</hi> Eneid. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſuch is <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> threſhold, it is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> it is <hi>ſuperliminarie crapulae, aut dementiae,</hi> a diſtracting cup, or a threſhold of madnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alcazar</hi> out of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> expounds the word elegantly according to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117577:12"/> the effects of drunkennes, a drunkard by reaſon of the dizzines of his head imagines the houſe moves, and will ſurely fall, whereas the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is in his own brain, the reeling and falling in his own bulk, the drunkard tumbles down in the dirt, while the houſe ſtands faſt; thus <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that ſeemes to totter only in the enemies fancy, and to fall only in his preſumption, ſhall ſtand faſt when her enemies lick the dirt, according to <hi>Davids</hi> caſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.2.</note> 
               <hi>When the wicked, even mine enemies came upon me, to eat up my fleſh, they ſtumbled and foll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the trembling of the enemies, the Lord makes <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſuch a cup to them;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 5 3.</note> we have a notable inſtance of it, even to the letter in <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzer,</hi> who in the midſt of his jollity, muſt needs ſend for the Veſſels and Cups of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> to drink wine with his Concubines; but mark, in the ſame houre came forth fingers of a mans hand upon the wall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, which made ſuch an Earth-quake in his heart, that his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance was changed, his thoughts were troubled, the joynts of his loynes were looſed, and his knees ſmote one againſt the other: was not here a cup of trembling? Thus was <hi>Ionathan</hi> &amp; his Armor-bearer ſuch a cup to the Philiſtins, when he climed up the rock againſt them, there fell a trembling in their Hoſt, in the field, &amp; among all the people, the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon and the ſpoylers they alſo trembled, and the earth quaked, for there was a very great trembling hebr. a trembling of God: God made this attempt, a cup of very great trembling to them. Its ſaid of the drunkards cup, that in <hi>praelia trudit inermem,</hi> it adds courage to the feeble and fearful; but this cup of ſpiritual drunkennes takes away cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and adds fear and trembling, it is a hornet from God that doth chaſe and affright the enemies of God.</p>
            <p>I will make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a cup of trembling: the Lord doth often pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh drunkards in their kind: the enemies of the Church who common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are bacchanalian and debauched Epicures, the Lord makes their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſin and delight, their ſnare and puniſhment. When the plundering <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malekites</hi> after ſome ſucceſſes,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.16.17.</note> and out-rages upon <hi>Ziglag</hi> and other places, they were drinking and dancing, in the nick <hi>David</hi> comes upon them, and mingles their blood with the blood of the grape, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed them, ſo that they were faine to vomit up all the ſpoyles and preys they had taken; pertinent alſo is that of <hi>Benadad, who with a mighty hoſt beſieged Samaria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.11.16. <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>even as he was drinking himſelf drunk in his pavilion, with the reſt of his Commanders, ſet his men in array againſt the City.</hi> But the Iſraelites came out and ſlue his Army with a very great ſlaughter. Right Honorable, was it not thus in our caſe with the enemy? He was carouſing and playing in his Tent, when he had
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117577:12"/> ſent his party againſt <hi>Dublin:</hi> he was ſo confident and inſolent, that he had already won the Citie in his preſumption; for he fell a diſpoſing of priſoners before hand, drinking healths to their owne ſucceſſes, and your confuſion. Are not theſe the Acts of men drunk, not with Wine onely; but with wrath? Yes, they had then taſted the top of the cup, which was the ſweeter, yet intoxicating, and muſt now take of the bottome too: Mark it in the effects and iſſue, a bloody iſſue to them; they ſtaggtred in their Counſels, they roared and raved in their purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they trembled in their undertakings, they ſtumbled in their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, they fell down to the ground in their ſhamefull diſcomfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and laſtly, they vomited up the greater part of the ſpoyle they had before ſwallowed, and fed themſelves with. Hence it is ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 28.7.</note> that Drunkards are ſaid to be <hi>ſwallowed up of wine,</hi> they are ſwallowed up of what they ſwallow: It's true in the letter, and myſtically ſo too,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 16.</note> their own morſell poyſons them. How doth the Lord aſſure that? <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I lay a ſtone in Sion;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 3.</note> this leads me to open to you the other Metaphor in the Text, in theſe words, <hi>In that day will I make Jeruſalem a burdenſome ſtone for all people,</hi> all that burden themſelves with it, ſhall be cut in pieces, though all the people of the earth bee gathered together againſt it. The 70. read it, <hi>A ſtone of treading down,</hi> ſo alſo the <hi>Syriac, or a ſtone of ſubjection and casting down:</hi> thus the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabick</hi> and the <hi>Chaldee</hi> come neere our Tranſlation, <hi>A ſtone of offence, or ſtumbling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ground of this Metaphor is taken from a cuſtome in all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Villages of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> which held in uſe till <hi>Jeromes</hi> time,<note place="margin">Hieronymus.</note> that for the exerciſe of their youth, they appointed great round ſtones: Theſe they were to lift, ſome to their knees, they that were ſtronger could lift them to the navell, or higher; even to their ſhoulders, and the crown of their heads, &amp;c. yet it came to paſſe, that many in lifting of theſe maſſive ſtones, by over-reaching and over-ſtraining, or by ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under their weight, were ſo ſtrained, bruiſed, and ſometimes their bones broken, that they became maimed by this meanes: <hi>They were ſnared and broken by the work of their hands;</hi> thus ſaith the holy Ghoſt. Many a one boaſting and preſuming of his ſtrength, ſhall be lifting and heaving at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they ſhal endevour to doe feats upon it, and take it into their hands, but it ſhould prove too heavy, and too tough a piece for them, they ſhall be over-reacht in it, and ſhall break their heads, their necks, their hearts, in the enterprize. I do not wonder now, the Prophet begins with, <hi>The burden of the word of the Lord</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the Lord who <hi>is a Sanctuary</hi> unto his people, is therein a <hi>ſtone
<pb facs="tcp:117577:13"/> of ſtumbling,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>and a rock of offence</hi> unto his enemies, he is a gin and ſnare unto them, and they ſhall ſtumble, and fall, and be broken, and ſnared, and taken. How this comes to paſſe, will preſently appear in theſe two enſuing concluſions; both which compriſe the generall mind of this Text, and hold forth a great truth unto us, very worthy our meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, very ſutable to this day, and ſo as comfortable to the people of God, as terrible to their adverſaries, all ſorts of men.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Obſerve.</hi>
               </note>It is ever fatall to aſſault the Jeruſalem of God. In their engaging againſt Jeruſalem, they doe but march the neareſt out to their owne graves: It's an evident token the Lord intends to blaſt a Perſon, Family, or Nation, if he permits them to advance and act hoſtility againſt his people: <hi>Jeruſalem is a cup of poyſon,</hi> &amp; <hi>a burdenſome ſtone unto her enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As the Lord is often exactly juſt in his recompence and retaliation of puniſhment upon malefactors, ſo he doth frequently obſerve and execute it upon his Churches enemies: both theſe are frequently taught in this Scripture; I will not handle them ſingly, but wrap them up together, as neere as I can, as belonging both to one.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.25. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.12.</note>The wiſe man ſaith, it is a ſnare for a man to devoure that which is holy, or a holy man, for the word beares either, and ſome read it in this latter. The word to ſwallow, or to devoure with open jawes, is attributed to perſecuting men; let us ſwallow them up alive as the grave, and vvhole as thoſe that go down into the pit, its meant of ravenous beaſts, birds, or fiſhes, that cruelly and greedily ſwallow their prey, wicked men in doing ſo, do but ſwallovv their ovvn banes, their ovvn poyſon: the vvord here for ſnare ſignifies the ſnare of a Hunter, or Fowler, perſecuting Nimrods, that hunt the poor ſheep of Chriſt vvith blood-hounds, that lay ſnares, and make pits for them that lye in vvait for innocent blood, and to catch men; vvretched Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, their own evils ſhall hunt them out; the game they chaſe and lie in vvait for, shall turn againſt them, their own dogs shall eat theſe Acteons, they shall be taken in their own nets: as vvhen the VVhale had ſwallowed Ionah, it was too hard a gob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet for him to digeſt, or hold it in his paunch, he muſt give him up again: vvhen Chedorlaomer and his party had plundered the Cities of the plain, and carryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay righteous Lot among the reſt: this one holy thing or holy man, vvas a ſnare to Chedorlaomar, he vvas his ruine. For his ſake onely did Abraham ingage, purſue, and recover all again, to the utter overthrow of 4. Kings that vvere Conquerors over five</p>
            <p>That of the Pſalmiſt is very full, when he would expres the abortive deſignes of wicked men againſt the righteous,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 7.15.</note> he doth it thus, he travelled with iniquity, conceived miſchief, and brought forth a lye, he made a pit, and is fallen into it. Thus wicked mens conceptions are not like thoſe of vvomen,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. Chryſologus. Cum in coelis inſanitis, non modo ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium facitis, ſed operam p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rditis.</note> but thoſe of Vipers, vvhich eat out their own bowels that bred them: therefore our Saviour calls vvicked men Vipers, of whom they write that the female in copulation bites off the males head, for this the young dig out the mothers belly to revenge the ſires death: Thus the Iewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h Synagogue which had perſecuted and killed the Prophets, their own Children deſtroy that Synagogue, their cruel Mother. <hi>I</hi> can but wonder that Heathen Seneca ſhould ever have any ſenſe of this; for ſaith he under the perſon of Soc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ates, againſt whom ſome in his age inveighed, vvhen you wax mad againſt Heaven, you do not only commit ſacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ledge, but looſe all your labour, and your ſelves alſo.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:117577:13"/>
            <p>God tells the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> that the people he had to deal with, were obſtinate, ſtiff necked, and brazen fore-headed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.8.</note> and they ſhould come and fight againſt him; but ſhould not prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, why? <hi>Behold I have made thy face ſtrong againſt their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and thy fore-head ſtrong againſt their fore-heads; as an</hi> Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, <hi>harder then a flint, have I made thy fore-head:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prada. in Ezek.</note> thus in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending with thee, they ſhall but break themſelves, <hi>indomabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis adamantis duricies, &amp;c.</hi> An <hi>Adamant</hi> is of invincible hardnes, it breaks the hammer, it dents the anvill, and overcomes the fire; ſo all our ſtrokes, and cruel expoſitions of perſecutors, ſhall not hurt or break a true Saint of God, but they ſhall break them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon them, as <hi>Dagon</hi> did upon the Arke, head and hands, craft and powers, a little before <hi>Ezekiels</hi> enemies are called Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, Serpents of poyſonous crooked ſtings;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 2.</note> but as they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly looſe their ſtings, ſo by cruſhing and applying it to the wounds, is the moſt effectual <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt its own poyſon; ſuch are the Churches virulent perſecutors, upon whom they looſe their malice and power, and through the wiſe diſpenſation of God, become medicins and preſervations by their cruſhing, to the people of God whom they afflicted.</p>
            <p>Thus, is that verifyed which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>When ſinners in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice thee ſaying, come let us lay wait for blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>let us lurck privily for the innocent without cauſe:</hi> they do but lay wait for their own blood, and lurk privily for their own lives: this is the iſſue of ſuch attempts (ſaith he) take heed of confederating with them: Hereto accords that of the Prophet; <hi>Woe to their ſoul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 3.9.10.11.</note> 
               <hi>for they have rewarded evill to themſelves: Woe to the wicked, it ſhall be ill with him, for the reward of his hands ſhall be given him:</hi> the word ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly implies, that wicked men by their certain miſcarriages in afflicting the righteous, and therein afflicting themſelves, are therein their own pay-maſters, in their own kind and coyne.</p>
            <p>Blind is that ignorance that ſees not how it is armed againſt it ſelfe;<note place="margin">Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius.</note> much like one that takes a Serpent in his hand to throw at another, wherein he cannot miſſe of being bitten with it him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or as one that taketh fire in his hands to burn another, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not avoid the ſcorching himſelf by it: thus malice alwayes fights againſt it ſelf, wounding more the Subject where it breedes, then the Object to which it would do miſchief: was not <hi>Goliah</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117577:14"/> with his own Sword: thus wicked men do but ſhew God a way (in perſecuting the righteous) and as it were, give him a preſident whereby his Juſtice ſhall proceed in their own execution. This may be gathered out of that teſtimony of our Apoſtle,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.4.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>a manifeſt token of the righteous judgement of God to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence tribulation to them that trouble you,</hi> the word is, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a pattern, precedent or Copy, as well as token, and is, as if God who by nature is meeknes and mercy it ſelf, and one who ſeemes ſcarce to underſtand (with Honour to the ſacred Majeſty,<note place="margin">Velas. in Ep. ad Phil. c. <hi>1.</hi> v. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> and in conformity to Scripture phraſe) which way to go about the work of puniſhment, ſeeming alwayes awke and averſe thereunto, he learnes the way of it from wicked mens actions againſt the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.8.</note>Obſerve that phraſe of the Prophet, <hi>He that toucheth you, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the apple of his eye:</hi> there are two things obſervable by us in theſe words. 1. the tender love of God to his Church, how it is garded and regarded by him:<note place="margin">Corn. in locum.</note> 
               <hi>the apple of the eye</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Daughter, to ſhew the Lord is as chary and tender of his people, as an indulgent Father or Mother is of a young beautifull Virgin againſt hurt or defloration, <hi>in the apple of the eye appeares,</hi> a little Image of a man, which the <hi>Hebrews</hi> calle <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a little man or Son: thus the Lord ſees his own Image in his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and they are ever in his eye: now who dare ſtrike Gods eye. 2. But how comes the Lord to ſpeak immediatly before, and after in the firſt perſon: why God, did he not ſay thus here, <hi>he that toucheth you, toucheth the apple of mine eye,</hi> ſo it ſhould run, and not his eye, properly if we apply it to Gods eye, as before; what if it be interpreted of the wicked mans eye: <hi>thus he that toucheth you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cyrill. Vatab.</note> 
               <hi>toucheth the apple of his own eye,:</hi> you ſee it agrees with the phraſe, and its a truth clear; for which I have named it, though I do not urge that expoſition, howbeit ſome interpreters are for it: <hi>ſic ſemper Eccleſiae perſecutoribus conatus ipſorum in caput reciderunt, &amp; tangunt ſuammet pupillam,</hi> even their neareſt and deareſt contentments, wherein God will obſerve his own Law, <hi>an Eye for an Eye, and a Sonne for a Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We cannot have a better inſtance then <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> ſo clear an il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration of this truth, and every way ſo accomodate to our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117577:14"/> purpoſe. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſay to</hi> Pharao, <hi>Iſrael is my Son, my firſt born,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.23.24.</note> 
               <hi>ſay to him, let Iſrael my Son go to ſerve me, if not, I will ſlay thy Son, thy firſt born:</hi> lock to it <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the Lord toucheth the apple of thine eye indeed, it was even ſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.29.30.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord deſtroyed Pharaohs firſt born, and all the firſt born of Egypt, upon this Pharaoh and the Egyptians riſe in the night, and there was a great cry, God had put out all their lights,</hi> can you blame their cry that night,<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 15.4</note> for ſo a Son and ſucceſſour is called, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.7. &amp;c. thus we ſee what it coſt <hi>Pharaoh</hi> for afflicting <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet were there many reaſons why the Lord ſhould puniſh him, beſides the foremenci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned he was a great Idolater, and Magician, he worſhipped the <hi>Cocrodile,</hi> and other abominable things; but the Lord pleads with him for none of theſe, onely for <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſeen the affliction of my people, and have heard their cry, by reaſon of their Task-maſters:</hi> this above all made God come down, and this proved fatall unto <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> Come let us deale wiſely ſaid he, <hi>i. e.</hi> let us deal cruelly and inſlave <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but was not this Prince of <hi>Zoan</hi> a foole in this, for that ſlavery was their increaſe, and their liberty, he would kill <hi>Iſraels</hi> males, they were ſaved, he loſt his own, their puniſhments are called plagues, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſtrokes, anſwering thoſe ſtrokes which the Task-maſters laid upon the poor <hi>Iſraelites.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull.</note> Who would not even pitty any perſon or parts in the world, engaged againſt Gods <hi>Iſralites,</hi> they are as forlorn, and ſuch as are a loſt Generation, ſo fatall is <hi>Iſrael</hi> to her enemies: this was obſerved even by the enemies of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and it muſt ariſe from obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how the Lord continually owned and avenged them, when <hi>Hammons</hi> plot did not take, and he came home melancholy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſt.</hi> 6.13.</note> 
               <hi>his wiſe men and Zereſh his wife told him, If</hi> Mordecai <hi>be of the ſeed of the Jewes, before whom thou haſt begun to fall thou ſhalt not prevaile againſt him, but ſhalt ſurely fall:</hi> An uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable <hi>Omen.</hi> What an unfortunate ſeed was this of the <hi>Jewes?</hi> It was ſo to all their enemies: they knew it, and could tell that <hi>Jeruſalem had been hurtfull unto Kings and Princes,</hi> a very bad City.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chald.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ezra.</hi> 4.12.15.</note> His meaning was, it had been very fatall, miſchievous, and unlucky unto Kings in their quarrels with it: it was <hi>ſeditious,</hi> and apt to inſurrections: i. e. it would not willingly endure the yoak of Ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rants, for that to them was ſedition: There was none of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions round about, but had their markes and maimes by medling
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117577:15"/> with <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> So fares it with all the Churches adverſaries in all ages.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> ad Scap. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>God forbid</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian) that we ſhould wiſh or work you any miſchiefe: yet we cannot but grieve that no City which hath ſhed our blood, ſhould go unpuniſhed, nor unrevenged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The example of <hi>Ahab</hi> is not lightly to be paſſed by: <hi>Ahab</hi> had committed many ſinnes in marrying <hi>Jezabel</hi> a foule Idolatreſſe, and by her a practizer and ſetter up of Idolatry: All this while <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> lives: but mark where he daſheth, and falleth irrecoverably upon <hi>Naboth</hi> a righteousman, he coveted firſt, and then killed, &amp; got poſſeſſion: By this unpolitick ſin he brings upon himſelf quick deſtruction,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.19, 20, 21.</note> and a recompence in his kind.</p>
            <p>Marke the Text: <hi>Thus ſaith the LORD, In the place where Dogges licked the blood of Naboth, ſhall Dogges licke thy blood, even thine.</hi> Which laſt words are added for the greater certainty; alſo to ſhew the law of retaliation, which God ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the puniſhment: and thirdly, that he would not ſpare him,<note place="margin" type="runSum">21</note> though a King: Thy blood, <hi>Ahab,</hi> even thine, ſhall goe for <hi>Naboths.</hi> But this is not all: <hi>But behold, I will bring evill upon thee, and will take away thy poſterity, and I will take away thy Houſe like the Houſe of Jeroboam the ſon of Nebat, and like the Houſe of Baaſha the ſon of Ahijah, for the provocations whereby thou haſt provoked me to anger, and made Iſrael to ſinne.</hi> By which ſinne is meant <hi>Ahabs</hi> Idolatry: but what is that to <hi>Naboth?</hi> This injury againſt <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi> makes <hi>Ahabs</hi> Idolatry to be remembred: the murdring of <hi>Naboth,</hi> and the track of his blood, led God along to all <hi>Ahabs</hi> other ſinnes againſt God, which before ſeemed forgotten: but his falling upon a righteous man, made a ſleepy Lion to awake, and teare him with his family in pieces, at leaſt 70. of them.</p>
            <p>Mark, when <hi>Ahabs</hi> 70. ſons were killed, they put their heads in Baskets, and brought them to <hi>Jezreel.</hi> Behold here the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of the puniſhment anſwers to the ſin here alſo: In <hi>Jezre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el Naboth</hi> was killed, the Baskets of grapes which he luſted after, are repayed with Baskets of heads, even of his own childrtn in the ſame place. <hi>Surely thou art righteous, O Lord, and juſt are thy judgements.</hi> It is the note of <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> on this Iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 7.37.</note>See another inſtance, Our Saviour Chriſt comming to dine at the houſe of one <hi>Simon</hi> a Phariſee, did not receive from him thoſe civilities which were uſually beſtowed in thoſe times and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries
<pb facs="tcp:117577:15"/> at entertainments. <hi>Simon</hi> ſhould have waſhed Chriſts feet ere he ſate down; he ſhould have received him with a kiſſe at his firſt comming in, he ſhould have anointed his head with oyle: all theſe things were wont to be obſerved at Feaſts, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments, and were due to our Saviour in courſe as his invited gueſt, but were denied him by the proud Phariſee; yet the Lord ſeemes to paſſe them over in ſilence: But loe this Phariſee doth not reſt there, but proceeds to finde fault with a poore penitent ſoule that came in love to Chriſt, to afford him what <hi>Simon</hi> had denied him; but he not being able to beare it, falls out with her, calls her ſinner, and taxes her for old miſcarriages. Mark,<note place="margin">Mat <hi>26.6.</hi> John <hi>12.</hi> ubi vides Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dae in Chriſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ejus res familiares delicta, rapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatem &amp; furta non an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tea objurga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta &amp; infamiae ſupplicio affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta quam ipſe ſanctae illi mulieri in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſus fuerit, &amp;c. <hi>Velaſq. in Ep. ad Phil. c. 1.</hi> Dan. <hi>3 2a.</hi> Dan. <hi>6.24.</hi>
               </note> the Lord Jeſus that was ſilent till now, can hold no longer: Now thou a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſeſt this poor creature that loves me, &amp; is beloved by me I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpare thee, take therefore a gentle rebuke for thy omiſſions of duty to me, which elſe I ſhould have buried in ſilence, thank thy ſelf <hi>Simon</hi> for this check; for thou haſt ſhewed me the way by thy quarrelling her that is my ſervant. The like befalls <hi>Judas Iſcariot</hi> for the ſame crime, who by his finding fault with the pious act of a devout woman, brought his own ſinnes to light, which till that time had been hid and covered, and might have long ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, had he not awakened Divine juſtice, by grudging at Gods ſervant. When <hi>Abimelech</hi> took <hi>Abrahams</hi> wife, was not his owne wife ſtruck with barrenneſſe, and was not his houſe plagued with great plagues for this cauſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.17? Mark how God threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him. <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. When the <hi>Sodomites</hi> that vexed the righteous ſoule of <hi>Lot</hi> from day to day, burned in the flames of unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall luſt at his dore, they were conſumed by the fire of hell out of heaven, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19. See how the puniſhment anſwers this ſinne. The ſame befell the enemies of <hi>Shadrach</hi> and his two companions, their enemies that kindled a fire to burn them, were burnt by the ſame flames. <hi>Daniels</hi> enemies were eaten by the Lions which they had caſt him amongſt to be devoured.</p>
            <p>Thus was <hi>Ammon</hi> recompenced by keeping <hi>Iſrael</hi> in bondage,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 49.1.2.</note> by becomming bondmen unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they dwelt in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as if <hi>Iſrael had no Sonnes or Heyres,</hi> as if <hi>Iſrael</hi> were eſcheated; for this the Lord ſent a ſword upon <hi>Ammon,</hi> and devoured him: <hi>Thus was Iſrael Heyre to them that were his Heyres,</hi> ſaith the Lord.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:117577:16"/>
            <p>The ſame befell them for their ſcoffing at <hi>Iſrael</hi> in her Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 25.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> ſaying, <hi>aha,</hi> clapping their hands, and ſtamping with their feet, that the ſame Judgement ſhould befall them.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Moab</hi> would needes curſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> by a ſorcerer, was curſed by him with his people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 22.23.24. <hi>cap. Jer.</hi> 48.26.27.</note> and the curſing Prophet ſlain with the Sword of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah gives Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ab a Cup of drunkennes to wallow in his vomit, and to become a deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:</hi> whats the reaſon, becauſe he had derided <hi>Iſrael,</hi> loe a cup of trembling for <hi>Moab. Haman</hi> got a Commiſſion to put the <hi>Jewes</hi> to death, and built a Gallows for <hi>Mordecai; Heſter</hi> got a Commiſſion to put <hi>Haman</hi> to death with his Sonnes, and he was hanged on his own Gallows;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſther. Cap.</hi> 6.7, 8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.11.</note> loe the exact ſeverity of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine juſtice upon his peoples adverſaries; for with what meaſure they meate to us, the Lord will meaſure to them again.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 18.19. <hi>Cap.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Zenacherib</hi> truſting in <hi>Niſroch</hi> his God, came up againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſlew the Children of God, he was ſlain by his own Children in the houſe of <hi>Niſroch</hi> his God. Thus the Lord comforteth <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 30.16.</note> 
               <hi>Behold, all that devoure thee, ſhall be devoured, all that ſpoyle thee, ſhall be a ſpoyle, and all that prey upon thee, I will give for a prey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.41.42. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 64.4.7, 8, 9.</note>Thus he that ſeeketh evil and vengeance, evil and vengeance ſhall come upon him: and this the Lord will recompence on his Churches adverſaries, as he ſolemnly profeſſeth: <hi>He will ſhoot ſuddenly with an Arrow againſt thoſe wicked Archers that ſhoot at his people, and will wound them: ſo ſhall they make their own tongues to fall upon them, and all men ſhall feare, and ſhall declare his doings.</hi> This hath made me the more copious in this, That God having executed the ſame acts of retaliating Juſtice upon your enemies, we may both wiſely conſider his doings, and declare thoſe works of God this day.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> Which conſideration may well put us upon a little ſearch of the ground of this proceeding in God.</p>
            <p>Its from that neare union and intereſt that the Lord and his people have in each other, whereby the Lord cannot but engage himſelfe to be tender of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.17.</note>They are as ſo many ſacred Temples unto God: Now <hi>If any man defile the Temple of God, him will God deſtroy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.</note>His people are his Body, and his Members, and his Fleſh and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117577:16"/> Blood: Now <hi>no man ever hated his own fleſh, but nouriſhed and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed it.</hi> Therefore if any hurt his body, members, or fleſh, he will require eye for eye, tooth for tooth, limb for limb, and life for life.</p>
            <p>They are the Lords ſons and children; he that wrongs them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.22, 23.</note> the Lord will ſlay their ſons, their firſt born.</p>
            <p>They are his Lambs, how tender is he of them, appeares in his three-fold charge to <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>feed them,</hi> and in bearing them in his Armes: will hee ſee them worried, and not avenge their blood?</p>
            <p>They are his brethren, mother and ſiſter;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark.</hi> 3.35.</note> it were unnaturall not to defend the lives and avenge the deaths of theſe? Nay, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this is one reaſon why he is called the <hi>Redeemer,</hi> or God;<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 35. <hi>Ruth.</hi> 3, 12, 13.</note> it is one of his Attributes, and he was properly a kinſman, and blood-friend, and he was ſuch a one which had <hi>jus vindiciarum:</hi> and ſhall we think this an empty Title? I tell you he will avenge his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reds blood, and that right ſpeedily.</p>
            <p>They are the Lords <hi>crown and glory, Iſai.</hi> 62.9. Nay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.3, 4.</note> and his very <hi>Jewels,</hi> will he ſuffer any to rifle his Cabinet; or pluck off the Crown from his head? who will not tremble at the thought of ſuch an attempt?</p>
            <p>They are the Lords Free-men; can we thinke he will endure them to be made ſlaves? How hath he then <hi>triumphed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.22.</note> 
               <hi>and led captivity captive,</hi> if he hath not made a perfect conqueſt?</p>
            <p>They are pure Virgins of the Lord;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2.</note> who durſt attempt the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity of his Virgins, or of his Spouſe, to kindle the fire of his jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie?</p>
            <p>They are all Kings and Prieſts to him through Jeſus Chriſt:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6.</note> therefore all anointed: therefore all ſacred, therefore he charges all the world not to touch them under that notion, and <hi>reproves Kings for their ſakes,</hi> the height of which prophaneſſe and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in his account, is a daring and provoking ſinne. Let us not think theſe Titles and Relations empty, they are the higheſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements in the world.</p>
            <p>Hence the Lord hath cloathed himſelfe with all titles of defence and ſafety. Take notice of one place where <hi>David</hi> in the day the Lord delivered him from all his enemies, calls God his <hi>Rocke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.2.</note> his <hi>Fortreſſe,</hi> his <hi>Deliverer,</hi> his <hi>God,</hi> his <hi>Strength,</hi> his <hi>Buckler,</hi> his <hi>high
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117577:17"/> Tower,</hi> and the <hi>Horn of his Salvation,</hi> and ſeverall attributes of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: which laſt alſo is a <hi>Horn of Salvation</hi> for his ſervants to puſh down their enemies. So we have God both a defenſive and an offenſive weapon to his people againſt their enemies, in that congratulation,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.29.</note> 
               <hi>Happy art thou O Iſrael, ſaved by the Lord, the ſhield of thy help, and the ſword of thine excellency:</hi> i. e. the moſt excellent ſword that his people can have, and that by which they excell and conquer their foes;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 44.6.7. <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.5.</note> therefore ſaid to be better then <hi>Bow</hi> or <hi>Sword,</hi> and more to be truſted unto.</p>
            <p>But that of our Prophet is a very high expreſſion, where the Lord ſaith, <hi>He will be a wall of fire about Jeruſalem,</hi> he had ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Jeruſalem ſhall be inhabited as Townes without Walls:</hi> Then they might object, How ſhall it be defended if it hath no Walls? Very well ſaith God, I will be inſtead of Walles, my ſalvation ſhall be Walles and Bulwarks,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note> this makes a ſtrong City; but this is not all, they are no common Walles that I will be to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gladio anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piti, flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meo et ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatili.</note> he will be a Wall of ſire about <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi> Alluding, ſaith <hi>Lactantius</hi> and others, to Paradiſe which was guarded by Cherubims and a flaming Sword, burning every way. Or perhaps alluding to ſuch as travell through Deſarts, where they have no fence in the night from ſavage Beaſts, but by making fires, which affrights a far off the devouring creatures: thus the Lord is to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Oh but will not this damnifie or endanger the Church within that fire? No, I will be glory in the midſt of her, fire without, and glory within. At the ſame time as the furnace was in <hi>Daniel,</hi> fire without burnt the enemies, but glory within to the three Worthies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.58.</note> for the Lord was there with them. <hi>Babylons</hi> wall is called a broad wall, it being 50. foot, others ſay 50. cubits thick, and of an incredible height, yet taken; we have a wall of water about us,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.28.</note> and wooden walls, yet all this is nothing to a wall of fire. It was ſaid of the <hi>Canaanits</hi> Cities that they were walled up to heaven, they fel down before <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but a wall of fire is more impregnable;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.17.</note> This the Lord threatned againſt that grand Tyrant <hi>Nebucadnezzar. The light of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall be for a fire, and his holy One for a flame: and it ſhall burn and devoure his thornes and his briers in one day.</hi> Thus you ſee the enemy is combuſtible ſtuff, as elſewhere tow, chaff, ſtubble and ſtraw: Thus ſhall they be to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in their attempts, and ſhe ſhall be fire unto them <hi>ver.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117577:17"/> v.</hi> 6. after my text, Surely the Lord will make it a hot day to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalems</hi> aſſailants.</p>
            <p>This ſhews Gods people to be invincible, becauſe all theſe titles of defence, as Walls, Tower, &amp;c. declare the Saints to be in God, that they dwell in, or within him: So the Pſalmiſt clearly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91.2 <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>He that dwelleth in the ſecret of the moſt high, ſhall abide under the ſhaddow of the Almighty.</hi> Now hence it followes, that thoſe who will at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tach <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> muſt firſt fight with God, and batter, ſtorme and break thorough him, ere they come at Gods people; think then that <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> aſſailants have the hardeſt pull of it of all others in the world. For <hi>who will ſet the bryars and thorns againſt him in battell, he will go through them and conſume them together. Go,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſing unto</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>a Vineyard of red wine. I the Lord do keep it, I will water it every moment: leſt any hurt it, I will keep it night and day. &amp;c.</hi> Marke <hi>Jeruſalem is red wine, i. e.</hi> generous and delectable to God, but poyſonous and dreadfull unto her enemies; and you hear the reaſon of it, <hi>I the Lord do keep it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us ſpeak a word to this reaſon of the point, according to the metaphor, in the third verſe, <hi>viz. of a Stone.</hi> How comes the Church to be ſuch a burthenſome and breaking Stone to her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe the Lord Jeſus is incorporated into their Walls both in the foundation and corners, and they as living Stones are cemented to him, and built upon him by his blood. This is that Rock againſt which neither the ſtormes,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4.5, 6, 7.8.</note> windes and waters, no nor the gates of hell can prevaile. This is that preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous corner Stone of God unto beleevers, but a Stone of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling and a Rock of offence unto the wicked.<note place="margin">Math. 21.44.</note> This is that Stone on which <hi>whoſoever falls ſhall be broken, but on whomſoever it ſhall fall it ſhall grind them to powder.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that little ſtone <hi>cut out of the Mountaine without hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.34.35, 45.</note> 
               <hi>which brake in peeces the iron, braſſe, clay, ſilver and gold, and when it had ſmote the Image, it filled the whole earth:</hi> This little Stone is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in his word and members, little and deſpiſed in the eye of the world, as <hi>Davids</hi> pebble was to <hi>Goliah</hi> and his Armes, but yet that which fell'd that Gyant to the ground:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.</note> ſo this little Stone ſhall breake Crowns, Swords and Scepters, even as Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheards, ſhall fill the earth and prevaile; It is the Lord that makes <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a burthenſome Stone to her enemies.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:117577:18"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> Is it ſo, That its fatall to <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> enemies to attach her, and doth the Lord puniſh ſuch machinations in their kind? Then let not <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> feat her enemies in their higheſt ruff, and threaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. There be 4 things that render an enemy formidable.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Policy,</hi> For they are in their generation more ſubtile then the Saints, they are Serpents and foxes, the Saints are Lambes and Doves. Yet fear not this, this cup here ſhall aſtoniſh and infatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate them. What a foole did that grand Oracle <hi>Achitophel</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as ſoone as ever he ingaged againſt <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Courage,</hi> yec fear not that, this cup ſhall be a cup of trembling to them; and ſhall make them ſhake as the leaves of a tree ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en with the wind.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Number,</hi> Fear not that neither, What ſaith the text? though all the people of the earth ſhall be gathered together againſt you, yet they ſhall be cut in pieces. And have you not had tryall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in all your conflicts, being ſtill over numbred by your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries; yet your Barley Cake tumbled downe the Tents of <hi>Midian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               <hi>Power,</hi> Be they a huge hoaſt of Cavalry and Infantry as the text hath it, do they glory in their ſtrength? and therefore ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach with contempt to your ſtrength; as <hi>Tobiah</hi> the <hi>Horonite,</hi> and <hi>Sanballat</hi> the <hi>Ammonite, What do theſe feble Jewes? if a Fox go up, he ſhall break down their ſtone wall.</hi> Yet up it went, and it became ſo ſtrong, that all the ſtrength they had could not demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, nor diſmantle it.</p>
            <p>Your adverſaries had all theſe foure advantages againſt you, <hi>Policy, Courage, Numbers, Power,</hi> yet your God fruſtrated all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> which became a cup of trembling, and a ſtone of ſtumbling to all theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> For Inſtruction, to behold as in a mirrhor this great truth veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to us this day, as by innumerable former proofs, ſo by that ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall inſtance, the cauſe of this ſolemnity. Let your rayſed medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions read over what God hath done for you, and behold this great Truth, riding triumph in all ages of the Church of God, that wicked men may heare, and feare, and that the righteous may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve and rejoyce; If we ſhould walk through the hiſtories of the Church,<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> we ſhould not onely finde <hi>Pilate</hi> for condemning Jeſus Chriſt to kill himſelf, <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Herodias</hi> that ſlew <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:117577:18"/> ending their dayes in miſery and baniſhment: Beſides the example of another <hi>Herod,</hi> who killed <hi>Iames,</hi> and impriſoned <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 12</note> and perſecuted the Church, he was ſmitten of God, and eaten of wormes in that very chapter; But alſo among perſecuting Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Domitius Nero,</hi> the firſt perſecutor of Chriſtians that was an Emperour,<note place="margin">Iuſtin.</note> proclaimed and condemned by the Senate to be whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to death, and drag'd through the Citie: for feare of which he ſlue himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Flavius Domitian,</hi> the ſecond Perſecutor, was ſlain,<note place="margin">Suet. in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. Speed. Chron.</note> and his body diſgracefully uſed by the Senate, his Scutcheons and Images thrown down, and they forbad any remembrance of him. Thus was he recompenſed in his Body and members, that mangled the Image, Body and Members of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The like befell <hi>Septimius Severus,</hi> ſlain at <hi>York, Caſſianus, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crinus, Antonius, Heliogabolus,</hi> Murderers and Monſters, all ſlaine; <hi>Alexander Severus,</hi> and <hi>Maximinus,</hi> likewiſe came to the ſame fatall ends. Behold the juſtice of God againſt thoſe murderers of Chriſts innocent ſervants, puniſhing blood with blood, according to the Law of retaliation. What ſhall I tell you of <hi>Decius,</hi> who raiſed the ſeventh perſecution, for which God ſuffered him to be aſſaulted for his life; for feare of which he threw himſelfe into a pit, and was never found.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gallus</hi> and <hi>Valuſian</hi> treading in his ſteps, were both deſtroyed by <hi>Emilian,</hi> a Captain. In thoſe dayes God plagued the Empire with an Epidemicall peſtilence, and many other heavy calamities, which the Heathens laid to the Chriſtians charge: But <hi>Cyprian</hi> writeth a confutation of that, and clearly proves it was their contempt of the Goſpel, and perſecuting of the Saints, cauſed thoſe evils.</p>
            <p>Theſe judgements fell alſo upon <hi>Valerian,</hi> who raiſed an eighth perſecution againſt Gods people: He was taken by <hi>Sapores</hi> King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> who made a captive of him, and his body a foot-ſtoole, treading on his neck when he went on horſe-back. A righteous judgement upon him who had trampled the truth, and profeſſors of it under his feet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aurelian,</hi> the ninth perſecuting Emperour, was terrified by a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117577:19"/> Thunder-bolt from heaven, and afterward ſlain, though he ſeemed ſomewhat to relent of his cruelty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diocleſian</hi> and <hi>Maximilian</hi> raiſed the tenth perſecution, both which quitted their imperiall dignity, and the latter of them ſlaine by the command of <hi>Conſtantine. Maximinus</hi> was ſmitten of God with rottenneſſe and vermine, as <hi>Herod</hi> was for waſting the body of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Famous is the death of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, who firſt ſubtilly, then openly perſecuted the Goſpel: he asked counſell of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Oracle which was deſtroyed by fire from heaven to ſmall powder; he encouraged the <hi>Jewes</hi> to rebuild the Temple, which was deſtroyed by an Earthquake, fire, and a mighty wind, at laſt he was wounded and died, crying out, <hi>Thou Ieſus of Galilee, thou art too hard for me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many ſuch inſtances may be added of the fatall ends of <hi>Arrian</hi> and <hi>Eutychean</hi> Perſecutors: But that of <hi>Phocas</hi> is very remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, who was the firſt that ſet up Antichriſt viſibly, by making the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> Univerſall Biſhop, and the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> head of all other Churches. This Emperour was beheaded, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, and his body given to the Souldiers to be burnt with fire.</p>
            <p>Notable is the example of <hi>Minerius,</hi> who being ſent to deſtroy the poore Chriſtians called <hi>Waldenſes,</hi> which he did by fire and ſword, felt the juſt vengeance of heaven by fire in his body, was conſumed with rottenneſſe, and voided blood in ſtead of urine, and died with great torments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, a famous Emperour for wiſdome and valour, yet daſhed againſt this rock of endevouring to deſtroy Proteſtants, was himſelfe driven out of his Empire, that endevored to drive out the Goſpel thence.</p>
            <p>To ſtep but on the other ſide, we ſhall finde <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Francis</hi> the ſecond of <hi>France,</hi> taken away by death, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan perſecutions there. Likewiſe the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> a cruell per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor, dying, gave breath to the poore afflicted Saints.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, a moſt perfidious and bloody Prince, dyed with great effuſion of blood from ſundry parts of his body.<note place="margin">Anno 1574.</note> Thus will the Lord have blood for blood, not ſparing the effuſion of Royall blood, to avenge the blood Royall of his children,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117577:19"/> whom he hath made Kings and Prieſts to himſelfe through Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.8. and which coſt the bloud of his deare ſon.</p>
            <p>I cannot paſſe by <hi>Henry</hi> the third of <hi>France,</hi> who was killed by a <hi>Iacobine</hi> Munke in that very chamber where the King had been chiefe in concluding the maſſacre of <hi>Paris;</hi> which maſſacre was ſo bloody and barbarous, that the very <hi>Spaniards</hi> at the treaty of <hi>Munſter,</hi> told the States of the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Nation had never done ſuch a Butchery againſt thoſe of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but abhorred ſuch acts; and that it was ſufficient to declare the genius of the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not come down lower to inſtance in later times, they are ſo infinite and ſo freſh, your own memories I hope are ſtored with them as ſo many Courts of Records, and your meditations often read them over. If it be not ſo, give me leave; as your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancer, to tell you, that you ought never to forget the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God written in blood, legible to all the world, that he will never let a wickedneſſe goe unpuiſhed which is acted againſt his people.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> Let us ſee the greatneſſe of the mercy which we commemorate this day, how God hath made <hi>Dublin</hi> a cup of trembling, and a burdenſome ſtone to her enemies in the ſiege. The greatneſſe of the mercy may be ſeen in theſe two particulars.</p>
            <p>There was very much of God in it, and little of man: whether you regard numbers the enemy had that advantage, whether his confidence, whether his ſucceſſes before: In a word, if you look on the beſieged as the laſt that were left to be eaten, that their adverſaries had it in conſultation to bind them back to back, and throw them into the Sea, that their ſuccours were delayed, and many diſheartning emiſſaries to perſwade the beleagred that no reliefe would come to them at all; that therefore they ſhould ſecure the Governour, and deliver the Citie; that then the Lord ſhould deliver the Citie from the enemy, arming a few beyond their own intentions, to deſtroy a huge Hoſt, let the Governours of <hi>Judah</hi> ſay, for this ſay the inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> ſhall be my ſtrength in the Lord of Hoſts.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Conſider the latitude and extent of this mercy, look not upon it as within the circumference of one ſingle Citie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nahum</hi> 3.12.</note> divers other Forts and ſtrong Holds followed, and come on ſtill dropping, as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117577:20"/> ripe Figs into the mouth of the eater. Many daughters attend the mother, or Metropolis; this great mercy is but the firſt fruits, and the earneſt of that which followes,</p>
            <p>Look on this mercy as that which reacheth three Nations, and all the true Iſrael of God, and the Generations to come; let us look on this mercy as one deadly wound to the Beaſt, and the falſe Prophet: a mercy though in compariſon of many great ones, not ſo great, yet ſuper-added to the quotient and catalogue, addes very much to the bulk of them, and to Gods glory; yet let me tell you, this victory and deliverance ſingly ſhines in its owne luſtre, without borrowing, and is able to ſpeak its own greatneſſe abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from others: Ask the broken enemy, their fruſtrated hopes, their ſlaughtered carcaſſes, their great loſſe ſpeakes it our great gain. Ask the trembling Citizens that were even in the paws of danger, and plunder, and death, and were delivered, they will ſay 'tis a great mercy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm</hi> 107.1, 2.</note> the redeemed of the Lord ſay ſo, <hi>That his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy endureth for ever.</hi> What need I ſay more? your ſelves that ſtand upon advantagious and higher ground, that ſee further and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer then us, that know the times what <hi>Iſrael</hi> ought to doe, that weigh circumſtances and conſequences in a right ballance, you have declared your ſenſe of it ſo high, that not a greater mercy on this ſide Egypt, hath been declared to Gods people. This mercy hath made ſuch an impreſſion upon ſome of your enemies, as was upon <hi>Saul</hi> when he told <hi>David, Bleſſed be thou my ſon David, for thou ſhalt doe great things, and ſhalt ſtill prevaile:</hi> or as was upon <hi>Balaam,</hi> when hired to curſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he bleſſed them, and ſaid, they were <hi>invincible, and ſhould ſtill doe valiantly:</hi> or as was upon <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> wife <hi>Zereſh,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>If Mordecai was of the ſeed of the Iewes, thoſe that began to fall before him, ſhould fall irrecoverably.</hi> This mercy to them is a owning by heaven of your paeſent power, your late changes and tranſactions which the world ſo much diſowned, and were ſtartled at.</p>
            <p>This mercy doth eclipſe and drown fore-going mercies, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Lord doth not only keep on his courſe of mercy to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but in a higher and more ſignall way; keeping the beſt wine till laſt, &amp; the moſt excellent Arts and Sciences till the concluſion. When the Trumpets ſounded louder and louder, then God came down.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.19.</note> When <hi>Joſhua</hi> compaſſed <hi>Jerico</hi> 7. daies, the Rams hornes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117577:20"/> ſounding; the laſt found had a ſhoot with it, and then <hi>Jericho</hi> walls fell down. Me thinks the Lord ſpeaking louder every day, his ſtroakes being ſtill greater, his diſcoveries being more glorious continually then before, what can it bode, but <hi>Babylons</hi> walls falling; the Lord coming down neerer unto us, even among us: See how the enemy, yea the earth trembles at his preſence. Shout therefore brethren his praiſes aloud, many a poor ſoul prayed and cryed aloud for this deliverance, and is heard by this return. Let our praiſes ſound as high, you know who got the victory by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God aloud, at which time the Lord ſet ambuſhes for his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 20.21, 22. and who knoweth what he is doing for us at this inſtant?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Add hereunto the nearnes of this mercy, many will look on this mercy as a thing afar off, becauſe done in another Land: but do we not know that our ſafety, and intereſt was even bound up in theirs? Is it not our out-works, which taken will ſoone ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us? Its the making up of a great banck, which broken will let in the enemy like a floud upon us. Have we not felt inundations from thence already? <hi>He turned the Sea into dry land, they went through the ſtoud on foot, there did we rejoyce in him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.6.</note> VVas not that deliverance far from <hi>David</hi> both in time and place; yet he ſaith, <hi>there did we rejoyce.</hi> Much more let us rejoyce now, as more near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intereſſed and related. Were not our hearts tuned to the notes of this Harp in the dolefull tunes of it? Let it be ſo now, in the joyfull tydings that it brings us.</p>
            <p>Again, learn to truſt thy God O <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he will defend thee in a ſiege and ſtreight againſt all the world. Never diſtruſt a Lord of Hoſts more upon any ſeeming diſ-advantages whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, they are but lures and ſnares to catch a preſumptuous dare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enemy:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9.10.</note> take an example yet to come after the thouſand years, Satan ſhall be looſed, and ſhall go out to deceive all the Nations of the four Quarters of the Earth, <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> to gather them together to battel, whoſe number is as the ſand of the Sea, and they went up on the breadth of the earth, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed the Camp of the Saints about, and the beloved City: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was there ſuch a league before <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> never did it ſuſtain ſuch a ſiege; but mark the end, fire came down from God out of Heaven, and devoured them, and then the Devil is caſt into the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117577:21"/> lake of fire and brimſtone, never look for war or ſieges more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that time: therefore truſt God for ever, and know, if you will believe, you ſhall ſee the glory of God yet daily, but I may not inlarge.</p>
            <p>Again, learn we hence, to wait on God, notwithſtanding ſome delayes, though he tarry wait for him, the adverſary muſt have his houre of the power of darknes: the waves muſt beat the ſhip, and fill it too while <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſleepes; yet know, he doth but ſeem to ſleep, his providence ever waketh, he that watcheth and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>Iſrael</hi> doth not ſlumber: what if <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> be beſieged, yet is it not therefore taken and deſtroyed. How hard were the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Jabeſh Gilead</hi> put to it by <hi>Naaſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.</note> almoſt to the putting out of their right eyes, and loſſe of liberty, yet they wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a little and were delivered: how greatly was <hi>Samaria</hi> diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, even to a great famine, ſo that the King ſaid, why ſhall I wait any longer; yet had they ſpeedy deliverance and plenty. 2 <hi>King</hi> 6. <hi>ult.</hi> and cap. 7.1.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>King. chap.</hi> 18.19.</note>How formidable was <hi>Zenacheribs</hi> numerous Hoſt before <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> of well nigh two hundred thouſand, that had conquerred and waſted all Countries round about, and by the blaſphemies of that great <hi>Rhodomont Rabſhakeh,</hi> all ſucceſſours ſeemed hopeles; yet <hi>Hezekiah</hi> waited, and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was delivered, and <hi>Zenache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribs</hi> Army deſtroyed, wait you on the <hi>Lord,</hi> wait I ſay on the <hi>Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is another conſectary which the Text holds out to us in the 5. verſe, that the Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> under God are the ſtrength of the Governours of <hi>Judah,</hi> the people of God in any place, are the ſtrongeſt Bul-wark to that place, why? becauſe the Lord of Hoſts is their God. O ye Governours of <hi>Judah</hi> think on this, how great have been your conteſts about the Militia of this Nation: now you have it, there is as great a care to mannage it with ſafety, and to its proper ends; but know this Worthies, you have a better Militia then the former, even Gods own people among you, this is your <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay you in your hearts, the Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be my ſtrength in the Lord of Hoſts their God: marke the Intereſt they have in God, is the Magazine and cittadel of their ſtrength and ſafety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> was called a Camp of Hoſt as they came up from <hi>Aegypt,</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:117577:21"/> and aske but <hi>Balaam,</hi> what he thought of them, when with an evil eye he took a proſpect of them. How godly are thy truths O <hi>Jacob,</hi> the Lord is among them, he hath as it were the ſtrength of an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorn,</hi> the people ſhall riſe up as a great <hi>Lyon,</hi> and ſtir as a young <hi>Lyon,</hi> he ſhall not lye down till he eat of the Prey, and drink the blood of the ſlain. <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.21, 22, 23. marke that, the Lord is among them, that's their ſtrength, they are among you, there's your ſtrength, theſe are your artillery,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 13.14. <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.5, 6</note> your great Ordinance; theſe are your Chariots and your Horſemen, as he ſaid of the Prophet.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall hurt theſe, fire goes out of their mouth, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes their enemies, as was ſaid of the witneſſes, thoſe have power to ſhut Heaven that it rain not in the dayes of their Propheſie, and have power over waters to turn them to blood, and to ſmite the earth with all Plagues as often as they will: it was ſaid of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, nemo impune laceſſivit populum Romanum,</hi> its more truly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to Gods people, none goes unpuniſhed that ſets himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. Know therefore where your ſtrength lies, in the holy people of God; be as Fathers to them, and as Nurſes, make much of them; do not think their or your ſtrength and ſafety lies in their diviſions, 'tis both your weaknes and nakednes, theirs and yours: call your Children together, make peace among them, favour them that do that work, and frown on them that divide: thus ſhall they be when ordered and united as terrible as an Army with banners.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Vſe."/> Give me leave in the laſt place, to add a word of Direction to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that Country, which the Lord hath given you livery and ſeizin of by this victory.</p>
            <p>An able Patriot udon this very ſubject, and Country,<note place="margin">Sr. I. Davies.</note> hath this rule. A barbarous Country is like a field over-grown with weeds and bryars: which therefore muſt firſt be throughly broken up with the Plough, and then immediatly ſown with good and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſeed; namely, good Laws and Diſcipline: in the going of the Plough of war and ſeverity, whatever you do with the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipals, who not unlike great waſters overſhadow, and deſtroy o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. I could deſire mercy towards the multitude ingenerall, that there be a rooting up rather of evill manners, then men; but that God may ſpeed the Plough, I beſeech you forget not a good
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117577:22"/> Miniſtery there, which in conjunction with a good Magiſtracy, may effectually pluck up every bitter roote that beareth gall and woormwood, as Popery and prophaneſſe, and ſow them with the precious ſeed of truth, and righteouſneſſe: if you ſhall not only ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilize, but ſpiritualize their wild barbariſme; if you ſhall indeavour to deſtroy the venemous things out of their hearts and houſes, as their land is ſaid to be free of them, if you labour to out them off, not only from forreigne intereſts abroad, but ſuch as are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign to Jeſus Chriſt; then ſhall they know the Lord Jeſus a better Protector to them, and Saviour then the Pope or <hi>Patricius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Right honourable, the Lord hath given you a City and a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, take heed you make ſurrender of it to him that gave it you, not for your ſelves, but for himſelf. Thus did <hi>Ioab</hi> when he won <hi>Rabba,</hi> he would not have it called after his name, but ſent to <hi>David</hi> to have the Crown ſet on his head, give you the Crown of <hi>Ireland</hi> to Ieſus Chriſt, much leſſe let <hi>Jim</hi> and <hi>Ohim</hi> rooſt there. Send al the pack of <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> traſh to <hi>Rome</hi> after the <hi>Nuncio.</hi> Let there be as much care taken for the Lord as for the land; for The ſpirituall eſtate of the poor people, as for the temporall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the rich: that they may look upon him whom they have cruelly pierced, and murthered in his Members: foraſmuch, as many of them did it ignorantly. Thus ſhall your victory become theirs, or rather the Lords; This will be a right improvement of ſo memorable and ſo great a mercy.</p>
            <p>And let not the great things done abroad, render you forgetfull of what the Lord hath done for you at home, and what you ought to do for him reciprocally. Two things were commended to us in Papers, to be recommended to your grave conſiderations; the cryes of the poor priſoners, and thoſe many files of Petitions that lye dormant in your hands, and were never read over. I doe not pretend to any ſuch knowledge, or power, which takes cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of particulars of thoſe two kinds forementioned; yet I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, let your eares be open to thoſe cries, both in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and alſo in other kindes, which reach up into Heaven, and beat loud Alarms in the Eares of Divine juſtice: Oh take care and heed, that the oppreſſions in the land, may not be ſuch as may cauſe the tears of the oppreſſed to ſpeak, They have no comforter, while on the oppreſſors ſide there is power;<note place="margin">Ecleſ. 4.1, 2.</note> ſome cry for bread
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117577:22"/> to feed their bodies, others cry for bread to feed their ſouls: ſome cry for juſtice, others for mercy: ſome ſinke under their burthens, others play the Task-maſters upon their brethren, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on them more loade: ſome grow rich upon others poverty, and ſome proud by others riches. Now, if you according to the truſt and power in your hands, unload heavy burdens, take off e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very yoak, and let the oppreſſed go free; If you make up the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches between brethren, and not ſuffer them to ſmite one another with the fiſt, if you countenance the truth ſetting it runne and be glorified, and give check unto conſcience waſting eror; if every way you are tender of the name of God, by righteouſnes and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs, the Lord will be tender of you and yours, and will build you a ſure foundation.</p>
            <p>And to end with the text; Take heed you do not daſh upon that Rock of fighting againſt God in any of his Members; Its your work to be tender of them, as its theirs to be tender of you: It may be <hi>Abiathar</hi> hath not carryed himſelf well to you in this great turne; yet remember they beare the Arke of the Lord God,<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.26.</note> and have been afflicted in all wherein you were afflicted. Let <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> example be your patterne, to perſwade, and even to inforce amity between divided brethren.</p>
            <p>I had many things to have added, but I would not abridge your other expreſſions of joy ſutable to ſuch a time, nor impede your emergent conſultations, nor impoſe upon your judgements. Let us ſhut up all by invocation and praiſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:117577:23"/>
            <p>Reader, by reaſon of the Authors abſence from the preſſe, thou art deſired to correct with thy pen theſe faults which eſcaped the Corrector,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Title page, for docet read docuit. p.</hi> 1. <hi>r. our. p.</hi> 2, <hi>r. of. p.</hi> 3. <hi>r. the for our. p.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>r. it. l. blot out Revel. p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>r. of. l.</hi> 13. <hi>for hoſts r. horſes. l.</hi> 21. <hi>r. Anakims. l.</hi> 23. <hi>for wars r. roſe. p.</hi> 6,<hi>r. the. p.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>r. ſpectators. l</hi> 19 <hi>for we r. be. p.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>grow r. therfore. l.</hi> 38. <hi>for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing r. encompaſſing. p.</hi> 18. <hi>l.</hi> 25. <hi>r. Gods eye. p.</hi> 23. <hi>for God r. good. p.</hi> 24. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>r. turning. p.</hi> 25. <hi>for go r. therefore. p.</hi> 27. <hi>r. voluſian. p.</hi> 29. <hi>blot out ſay in l.</hi> 24. <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>l.</hi> 36. <hi>for arts and ſciences r. acts &amp; ſcenes. p.</hi> 31. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>r. ſhout. p.</hi> 31. <hi>l.</hi> 36. <hi>for league r. league r. p.</hi> 32. <hi>l.</hi> 21. <hi>for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors r. ſuccours p.</hi> 33. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>for godly r. goodly, &amp; for truths r. tents. p.</hi> 33. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>r. upon, p.</hi> 34. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>for out r. out. p.</hi> 35. <hi>r. errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:117577:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
